<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The contre-Guyse vvherein is deciphered the pretended title of the Guyses, and the first entrie of the saide family into Fraunce, with their ambitious aspiring and pernitious practises for the obtaining of the French crowne.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12506</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120871</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856064</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856064</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21582</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02375)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21582)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 304:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The contre-Guyse vvherein is deciphered the pretended title of the Guyses, and the first entrie of the saide family into Fraunce, with their ambitious aspiring and pernitious practises for the obtaining of the French crowne.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Iohn VVoolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>French original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Guise, Charles de, --  Cardinal de Lorraine, 1525-1574.</term>
               <term>Guise, House of --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21582:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21582:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Contre-Guyſe:</hi> Wherein is deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phered the pretended ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>tle of the</hi> Guyſes, <hi>and the first entrie</hi> of the ſaide Family into Fraunce, <hi>with their ambitious aſpiring and per</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious practiſes for the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the French Crowne.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Imprinted by Iohn Woolfe, 1589.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21582:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21582:2"/>
            <head>The Contre-Guyſe: CONTAINING <hi>the entry of the ſayde Family into</hi> Fraunce, with their ambitious aſpirings, and <hi>pernitious practiſes for the obtaining of the crowne thereof.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hings naturall, ſaith Plutarch, are ſubiect to a continual fluxe of generation and corruption, and he onely immutable, who neuer had beginning, neyther ſhall haue ending. Man, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his body, hath certaine periodes, wherein he euidently admitteth alteration, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſame doth increaſe and decreaſe, as the flower of age is ſwallowed vp in olde age; youth, in the flower of age, infancie in youth, and childhood in infancie. Herein dooth nature reſemble the image of man, and man the figure of euery commonwealth, which how excellent and beautifull ſoeuer, doth by degrees wax old,
<pb facs="tcp:21582:3"/> as matter ſubiect to the brooke of liquide na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Antiquitie hath knowne ſome well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in mightines, and triumphing in glory, but any that haue withſtoode the courſe of time, hath no man ſeene, or euer ſhall: For as our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies doo come to be diſſolued, eyther through outward bruiſes, proceeding of extreme vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of ſtripes, or bad proportion of humors, or finally by beeing broken and worne with olde age: euen ſo likewiſe doo commonwealthes and publike affaires growe to their laſt periode, and decay through diuers accidents: Some are ouerwhelmed and drowned in deſolations, which ouerflow all: ſome kindled with fire of ciuill diſſention: and other ſome vndermined by time, doo ſo growe to the laſt periode of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, and as a perſon worne with age doo take end. To indeuour therefore to ſettle the courſe of worldly affaires, were, with the Giants to ſeeke to skale the heauens. But to take ſuch or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the alteration of the commonwealth may gently and naturally take effect: to ſeeke all meanes to yeeld it ſure footing: to ſpread the ſayles to all windes, for the bringing of it to the harbour of ſafegard: If it bee ſicke, to play the phiſition: if it ſtumble, to lend it a hande: if the ſight of it fayle, to reach it ſpectacles: and finally, if it be ſtriken in yeares, to become the ſtaffe of the old age thereof: all theſe are
<pb facs="tcp:21582:3"/> the partes of a good and louing nature, yea, of ſuch a nature, as is vtterly free from all Cinicall curriſhneſſe; and to ſay the truth, is no more but the diſcharge of our dueties vnto our country.</p>
            <p>This is the reaſon, O ye Frenchmen, why now that ſome for the patching vp of the olde broken walles of their aunceſtors ambition, doo goe about to choke vp our quietneſſe, in tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning forward their curſed and execrable pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, with the expences of our goodes, blood, and liues. I cannot, as one ſtanding vpon the firme land, gaze vppon the ſhipwracke of my country, but ſeeing it toſſed, and floting in daunger, muſt needes caſt foorth the laſt ſacred ancker of my ſelfe, which is, a bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of free ſpeech: and becauſe in humane accidents the diſcourſe muſt be deriued from the originall, marke now the ſpring of our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable calamitie.</p>
            <p>In the time of Lewis the 12. ſurnamed the father of the people, Claude of Lorrayne, or rather of Vaudemont, ſet foot in France, where he ſtraightwaies began to remooue euery ſtone for the laying of the foundation of that mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, wherevnto we now ſee his ſucceſſors aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and did ſo dazle the eies of the French with a falſe ſhew of his wealth, that in the yeare 1512 about the feaſt of God at Paris, in the hoſtel of
<pb facs="tcp:21582:4"/> Eſtampes, hee marryed Anthoinel of Bourbon, daughter to Frauncis of Bourbon, and Mary of Luxembourg. But Frauncis Duke of Valois, and Earle of Angoleſme, by the deceaſe of the ſayde Lewis comming to the crowne, and beginning to ſmell out the humour of this ſtraunger, helde him ſhort, &amp; diuiding the chiefeſt offices of his<note place="margin">Du Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay. lib. 1.</note> houſe, then void, ouerſlipped him. The Duke of Bourbon was made Conſtable, the Earle of Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſme Gouernour of the Ile of Fraunce, the L. of Lautrec Gouernour of Guyen, the L. of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſe Marſhall of Fraunce, the L. of Boiſſy great Maiſter, Anne L. of Montmorency, and Philip Chabot the Kings two fauorites: Of Claude of Lorraine there was no ſpeech, his winges were yet too ſhort to ſoare to ſuch highneſſe, vnder the ſhadow whereof hee lay a whyle hidden, which no whit diminiſhed his hope of happy ſucceſſe. But Ambition, which (as ſayth Thuci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dides)<note place="margin">Plutarch in his treatiſe, whether an olde man, &amp;c.</note> neuer dyeth in man, cauſing him ſtifly to withſtand fortune, taught him ſo ſlily to blot out whatſoeuer ſiniſter opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the king had concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of him, that after many turnings &amp; toſſings, he was finally take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into houſhold, &amp; made great hunter, which office had long continued in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of gentlemen of meane account: vnder<note place="margin">Du Tillet chap. of the great hunter &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alconer.</note> Charles the 6. it was adminiſtred by Lewis of Orguechin: vnder Lewis the 11. by Iuon of Fou: vnder Lewis the 12. by the Lords of Chenetz &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:21582:4"/> Rouuille, whereby it is to be preſumed, that this Lorraine was then farre off from the greatneſſe pretended by his ſucceſſors, and that it could not be ſaid of him, that he made way to dignitie by the countenance of his aunceſtors, as by a certaine Romaine it was obiected to Piſo: but rather that of a courſe haire &amp; ſmall credit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe opened a way to himſelf to honor through craft and guile, yea, like a wily Foxe, as is ſaid of Pope Boniface the 8. For in truth hee ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly purſued the point of his good hap, and from time to time ſo ſoundly huſbanded the kings fauours, that according to the diuers oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences of affaires hee executed ſundry func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. For about the yeare 1515, the king leuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">Du Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay. lib. 1.</note> an Army for the conqueſt of Millan, got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his pay 6000 Allemaigns, vnder the leading of the Duke of Guelderland, who ſhortly after hearing that the Brabanders had entred his country, poſted home to releeue his owne peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and left his charge to Claude of Lorraine, Lord of Guiſe: neuertheleſſe in the yeare 1521, in Admirall Boniuels voiage into Nauarre, he had the conduct onely of 2500 launce-knights, and in the yeare 1522, ſeruing in Picardy vnder the Lord of Vendoſme, he had the charge onely of one company of men at Armes: But the wind turned ſo fauourably for him, that in the yeare 1523, when the Lord of Trimouile was made
<pb facs="tcp:21582:5"/> gouernor of Picardy, he left to him the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Burgondy, whereto the next yeare was adioyned Champaigne, by reaſon of the iourney into Italy, whither the chiefeſt of Fraunce ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed the King, at whoſe returne this Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine did ſo cunningly bend his affections, that in Ianuary 1527, hee erected him his village of Guyſe into a Duchie, &amp; in tract of time Charles Duke of Orleance, the kinges yonger ſonne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent with a great Army to ground and caſt the burden of the warres vppon the Duchie of Luxembourg, had for his chiefe Counſellors the Lords of Iametz and Guiſe. Thus may wee ſee this Lorraine crept very high for a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of baſe golde: but ſuch was the kinges plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whoſe power appeareth in exalting the baſe, enriching the poore, and increaſing the ſmall: ſuch was his fauour, yea ſuch, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there ſtill reſted in him ſome ſiniſter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of this ſtraungers humours, yet would he not neuertheleſſe depriue him of any of his offices or dignities, ſo that he proſecuting his good hap, obtained ſo ready entry into the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of king Henry the 2. that his children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing honorably appointed, he procured Aumale to be erected into a Duchie, in the yeare 1547. &amp; ſo, to be briefe, being growne rich in goodes, alliance, and honour, as beeing Duke of Guyſe and Aumale, Peer of Fraunce, and gouernor of
<pb facs="tcp:21582:5"/> Burgundy, hee deceaſed the 18. of Aprill 1550. in this like to M. Perpenna, who, as witneſſeth Valerius, was Conſull before hee was Citizen: but vnlike in that, that as ſaith the ſame author: <hi>The life of Perpenna was triumphant, but his death ignominious, through the lawe Papia in his fathers perſon, who being naturally a ſtraunger, was baniſhed Rome for vſurping the priuileges of Romane Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens,</hi> whereas contrariwiſe this mans children continued their fathers triumphes, yea as it was ſaid of Perpenna, They haue with a miſchiefe rooted themſelues in a forraine land.</p>
            <p>This was the ſtraunger, O ye Frenchmen, to<note place="margin">Plut. in his nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Plut. in the life of Silla. Plut. of brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue.</note> whom you might haue ſaid, as the Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians ſaid to Philip king of Macedon, that they would not he ſhould come into their land, either as a freend or as a foe: this is that wretch, of whome yee may ſay as of Sillaes father, that he could ſcarſe bee honeſt, ſeeing hee grew ſo ſoone rich: this is that vagabond, on whom we ſhould practiſe the ſaying of Theophraſtus, importing, that we muſt not loue ſtrangers to proue them, but proue them to loue them: this is that great hunter, that faulconer that hath brought vp his children after the manner of rauenous fowles, who with their ambition, as with a crooked beake, doo rent poore Fraunce in pieces, &amp; with ſharpe tallants do ſeeke to ſeaze vpon this eſtate: O wiſe and valiant king Frauncis, how neere a
<pb facs="tcp:21582:6"/> true prophet came you, when you foretold that if euer this wretches oſpring tooke footing or ſure root in Fraunce, it would ſtrip the kings into their doublets, and the people into their ſhirtes: for wee may geſſe at that which is to come, by that which is eyther preſent or paſt, conſidering that nothing is done without cauſe, neither can any thing bee foreſeene without ſome reaſon preceding. This Oracle might haue made vs to haueſtood vpon our gard, but who can auoyd deſtinie?</p>
            <p>The children of this Claude of Lorraine bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fatally deſtinate to the ſubuerſion of this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, haue enioyed the moſt part of the fauours of Court vnder Henry the 2. at whoſe coronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they ſo cunningly exalted their ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they got the chiefe point of honour and preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence before the Duke of Montpenſier, a prince of the bloud, as by the acte reſerued by du Thier Secretary of commaundements, the 25. of Iuly 1547. which alſo in the yeare 1559. they put in practiſe at the annointing of king Frauncis the 2. in reſpect, ſaide they, of the antiquitie of their Peeryes, wherein muſt bee more regard of the repreſented then of the repreſenting, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding<note place="margin">Du Tillet in his col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of the great men of France.</note> it had beene otherwiſe adiudged by a decree of the parliament of Paris, betweene the Dukes of Montpenſier and Neuers in Iune 1541. Hauing wonne this barre and title of greatnes
<pb facs="tcp:21582:6"/> ouer France, they began vpon the earneſt peny of their credit more &amp; more to diſplay the wings of their ambition: and in truth, as the defect of veſſels cannot be ſeen ſo long as they ſtand emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but when licour is powred into them: euen ſo rotten and corrupt minds can no longer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale themſelues, when they haue once attained to authoritie and power, but muſt needes burſt foorth and diſplay themſelues in their couetous affections and inſolencies, as may bee noted in theſe vntimely births of fortune: For about the yeare 1548, when a certaine aduocate of the parliament in his plea for the Duke of Guyſe, had giuen him the qualitie of a Prince, which by a preſent decree was razed, it ſo ſet them out of ioint, and filled them with bitternes, that the Cardinall Charles of Lorraine neuer left remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing euery ſtone for the diſplacing of Preſident Liſet, vntill hee had compaſſed the ſame in the yeare 1550, though vnder an other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. Afterward, for the further aduauncing of their ambitious drifts, and the nearer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the Cantharides, who, as Plutarch ſaith, doo ſtill creepe into the pureſt wheat and freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt roſes, they entered liſtes with the Lord Anne of Montmorency, vppon whome after ſundry croſſings, and vnder fauour of his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which fell in the yeare 1557, at the battell of Sainct Laurence, they ſo encroched, that the
<pb facs="tcp:21582:7"/> king gaue to Francis of Lorraine a commiſſion of Lieutenant general, wherat the Conſtable, as a wary perſon, and one practiſed in ſeruing the time, could very well winke, and ſo ſet a faire countenance vpon a fowle game. But in tract of time the king grew to bee ſo glutted with the faire ſpeeches of theſe Lorraines, and their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate baying at the chiefe offices of the crowne, that as one not troubled with any le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargie of mind, but euen to the quicke feeling ſome drifts of their ambition, he reſolued vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to rid his hands of ſuch &amp; ſo ſubtil husbands, and to driue them from about his perſon, yea, euen out of his dominions, wherein they had through their crafty conueiances fattened them ſelues, euen to the great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt of the Queene now the kings mother, who through their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions was at the point to haue beene ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reiected, and to the deſolation of the French nation, among whom they haue ſerued onely for bellowes to kindle the fire of ciuil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſo that ſince they came to be our gueſts we may exclaime of Fraunce, as did Ageſilaus<note place="margin">Plut. in his nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> of Greece, when hee heard of a cruell conflict neere to Corinth betweene the mutinous Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians one againſt another. Oh vnhappy Greece, who with their owne handes haue made away men ynow in one day of battaile to haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all the Barbarians togither! But the kings
<pb facs="tcp:21582:7"/> purpoſe was preuented by Gods prouidence, who not willing to take that ſcourge from vs, made France a widow of this good king in Iuly, 1559, &amp; ſo gaue vs ouer for a pray to the intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable ambition, inſatiable auarice, and raging cruelty of theſe ſtrangers, who raigning ouer vs vnder the ſhadow of king Francis the 2. and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the fauour of his minoritie plaied open play againſt the Princes of blood, yea, and ſet ſo ſure foot vpon the throat of this eſtate, that Fraunce was the bloody ſcaffold, good Frenchmen the martyrs, and theſe Lorrains, moſt cruell, felloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and vnmercifull hangmen. This ſtorme might immediatly after the deceaſe of K. Henry haue beene foreſeene: for whileſt the Princes of the blood and chiefe officers of the crowne kept their maiſters bodie at the Tournelles the kings houſe in S. Anthonies ſtreet, where euery thing ſounded of ſorrow and mournfull ſonnets, theſe gentlemen triumphed at the Louure, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had caried the king, about whom they commanded at pleaſure, and vnder the cloke of tutorſhip made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues way to the ſouereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as did Tarquin the 1. who vnder the like pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence wreſted the Romane kingdome out of the hands of Ancus Martius children, or as Stillico<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Ruffin, who being tutors to Arcadius &amp; Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius, brought the Romane Empire into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion. But what ingratitude, what in humane
<pb facs="tcp:21582:8"/> vnthankfulneſſe was it to ſtand with drye eyes, when all other accompanied the king with wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and teares? What tiranny, to bend their maſters minoritie to their paſſions? What im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencie, to in trude vpon the authoritie of the Princes of the blood? The law (by the common aduiſe of the three eſtates aſſembled at Tours, Anno 1484. decreed) commaundeth, <hi>If the crowne ſall to a pupill the 3. eſtates muſt be aſſembled, and by them the king prouided of a counſell for the gouernment of his nonage:</hi> The cuſtome is, <hi>The Princes of the blood haue the firſt place in this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,</hi> as it fell out, when at the deceaſe of Lewis the 11. Charles the 8. at the age of 14. yeares came to the crowne. The Romane lawes will, <hi>That hee that affecteth or intrudeth himſelfe into any tutorſhip, ſhould be reiected as ſuſpect.</hi> Beſides, it is a generall, ſacred and inuiolable rule, <hi>That no forraine Prince hold degree in France.</hi> But what can reaſon doo in rage, or cuſtome among diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders? what can right doo where force beareth ſway? or of what force are lawes among mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, blood, and tiranny? hauing aſſured them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of his Maieſties perſon, they played their game ſo cunningly, that a new gard was eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed vnder the Seneſchall of Agen: Diana of Poictiers Ducheſſe of Valentinois, baniſhed the Court: Bertrandi Preſident of Tholouſe, vnto whome Henry the 2. had committed the ſeales
<pb facs="tcp:21582:8"/> of Fraunce, flatly deferred, though pacified vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hope of better: The ſuperintendence of the Treaſurie taken from Auanſon, and vnder co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of good husbandry, the faithfulleſt ſeruants of the crowne beeing diſplaced, the gate of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was open to none but the confederates of two ſtraungers, who for their owne particular profite encroched to themſelues all publike af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, euen as the winde <hi>Coecias,</hi> which (as it is ſaide) draweth the clowdes to it, and furniſhed the law with men of like ſtuffe as themſelues, &amp; ſuch as were vowed vnto the execution of their bad purpoſes: as alſo at the ſame time they ſtrengthened their owne faction with the ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Marſhals Briſſac &amp; S. Andrew, &amp; the Cardinal of Tournon, the Coneſtables ſworne enemy. Putting in practiſe alſo Andronodorus counſaile (who abuſing the minority of Hierom king of Sicill, whome he purpoſed to rob of his eſtate, perſwaded him to baniſh the chiefe of his Realme from the Court) they did vnder the kings auow craftily diſperſe all thoſe that might haue croſſed the courſe of their fortune, &amp; with whome they could by no meanes beare, not ſo much becauſe of the difference of their natures, as for that the French cannot put on the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raines nature, or the Lorraine the Frenchmans, according to the ſaying of Cicero, ſpeaking of the ordinary controuerſies betweene the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb facs="tcp:21582:9"/> Conſuls and Tribunes. <hi>The fire of ciuill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention is kindled betwene them, not ſo much through diuerſitie of qualities, as by contrarietie of humors &amp; complexions.</hi> And thus was the Prince of Condé<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent into Flaunders, vnder pretence of ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening the amitie with king Philip, and after him the Prince of Roch-ſur-yon, who at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne was choſen togither with the Cardinal of Bourbon, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct La. Elizabeth into Spaine: The Duke of Montpenſier was furniſhed with the gouernment of Touraine, but they appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chauigny to be his Lieutenant, with ſuch authoritie, that the Prince had onely the title: The Conſtable had the gentle thumpe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other trauerſes loſt the office of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter, which wound was afterward renewed in the controuerſie for the countie of Damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>martin, which Frauncis of Lorraine Ceſſionary of Rambures pretended to carrie away. The court beeing thus become a widow of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the blood, and naked of the braueſt of the French knights, the Guyſians began to build vp their houſes with the decay of many other, yea in ſuch ſorte as they ſpared neyther freend nor foe, Papiſt nor Proteſtant, ſpirituall goodes nor temporall: witneſſe the Countie of Nantueil, and the chiefe benefices of the Cardinall of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noncourt, a frend to their family: witneſſe the goods of the Marquiſe of Neelle, &amp; of the Lord
<pb facs="tcp:21582:9"/> of Grignan, the caſtle of Meudon, the houſe of Marchais, &amp; the land of Cheureus: witneſſe the Monkes of Monſtier<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> endé, whom the Cardinall thruſt out, &amp; burned al the titles of their church for the enriching of his houſe of Ginuille: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Storier of S. Diſier, whom he cauſed to be burned for a Lutherian, notwithſtanding, by the teſtimonie of all the country, hee went or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily to Maſſe, ſo as the poore man might ſay as Quintus Aurelius, who finding himſelfe in the roule of thoſe who by placards were bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, notwithſtanding he neuer medled with the<note place="margin">Plut. in Silla.</note> warres of eyther Marius or Silla, cryed out, <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las my houſe at Alle killeth me.</hi> Shall I come to the concluſion and laſt acte of the Tragedy? Shall I open a wound which yet bleedeth? Things grew to that paſſe, that by the Cardinall and his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all lawes &amp; good decrees were taken down: the Parliaments of the Realme diſhonored, and euery way derided: the people choked with ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny: the Prince of Condé impriſoned at Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leance for fellonie, falſly inuented, as afterward it is declared by a decree of the priuie councell, dated the 13. of March 1560. and by two decrees of the court of Parliament: the La. of Roye im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned at S. Germaines in Laye: the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles houſe appointed to ruine and ſubuerſion: his nephew the L. d'Andelot diſcharged of the office of Coronell of the French footmen: the
<pb facs="tcp:21582:10"/> Cardinall of Arminacke baniſhed the court: the Vidame of Chartres miſerably detained in the Baſtille: the priſons full of poore innocents: the ſkaffolds red with blood: the gibbets ordinarie: fiers kindled: all was but deſtruction and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: but robbing of houſes: proclamations of baniſhments: and moſt cruell executions: in peace we bare the effects of a bloody warre, and in calme and faire weather the face of Fraunce was horrible and fearefull: and yet do we ſuckle vp theſe hangmen with our blood: we feed them with our goods: we make them triumph in our ſhame, and to them onely are the gates of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors open: but why doo we not rather ſpeake as did Rabirius by his aduocates mouth? <hi>Grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hus</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>would rather haue ſuffered 1000. moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell deaths, then haue ſeene the hang man aſsiſtant in his court, who by the lawes of the Cenſors, ought to haue no habitation in Rome.</hi> And yet is the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as the miniſter of iuſtice, more tollerable then theſe, who in their bloody executions were not authoriſed, but by their owne ambition, whereto they had ſo ſmoothed the way, that there wanted no more but with open title to proclame themſelues kings. For, to giue prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and the treaſury: to make lawes, &amp; to breake them: to determine of warre and peace: to giue and take away offices: to ſend embaſſages: and in all things to haue the laſt voice, was common
<pb facs="tcp:21582:10"/> among them: what then did they want more then the name, annointing, and crowne? hauing alſo laid their principall plot vpon certaine ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious miniſters of their paſſions, they drewe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace to the ſoueraignitie, if God, euen God tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the preſeruer of France, had not caſt a blocke in their way anno 1560. by the kinges death, whoſe name they made their buckler to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of himſelfe and his eſtate: and vnder whoſe pretenſe they made the rampier of the vnruly effect of their immoderate paſſions, ſo that not beeing yet throughly fortified with all things neceſſary for their purpoſes, they ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the mid way, and their affaires ſuffered a chaunge. But now, Oye Frenchmen, looke vpon your kinges funeralles: his body without any pompe or ſolemnitie was conueied by Sanſac and Broſſe to S. Denis, where it was ſimply bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. Bluſh ye Guyſians, yea for ſhame hide your ſelues, when you heare that Hanniball beſtowed honorable funerals vpon the Conſul Caius Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius, whom he ſlew at the lake of Peruſe: that Lucius Cornelius did as much for Hanno the generall of the Carthagineans, and Marcus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius vpon his enemy Arcilaus: and yet you without any pompe doo commit to the earth the body of ſo great a king, yea of that king that raiſed you to the tipe of honor. Hide, hide your ſelues, I ſay, when you vnderſtand that Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:21582:11"/> ſpent 6. millions of gold vpon the funerals of Epheſtion, and yet you that haue beene ſo prodigall of the common-wealth in your owne priuate affaires are become ſo nigardly in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concerning the funerals of one of the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt monarckes of the earth. The Emperor Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus euen in winter time came from Rome to Pauye before the body of Druſus: Tiberius did aſſiſt the funerals of Auguſtus, Caligula thoſe of Tiberius, and Nero thoſe of Claudius: The kinges, Childebert and Clotaire led the body of Queene Clotilde from Tours to Paris: Lewes the groſe that of king Philippe the firſt, from Meleun to S. Bennets vpon Loyre: and Phillip the 3. holpe to cary the Biere of S. Lewes from Paris to S. Denis, and yet you vnthankfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, you muſhroms of a nightes grouth can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not vouchſafe to ſet one foote out of the gates of Orlea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for the leaſt ſeruice of pietie to your maiſters body<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; yet muſt you be tearmed the Zopires of our kinges, the corner ſtones of this realme, the eyes, the ſinewes, and the vaynes of this body! but rather indeede the tirants of our kings, the ſcourges of the poore people, &amp; the ſpunges of our treaſures: you I ſay, who haue no other God but ambition, no other king but A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarice, ne any other religion then deſire of gain, after which we ſee that you are fleſhed as Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens after cartio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who rather then to leaue your
<pb facs="tcp:21582:11"/> hold will ſometimes caſt your honour at your backs: witneſſe the lies that the late Lord prince of Condé in the yeare 1559. gaue you, when he offered to forget his degree &amp; qualitie of prince to vpholde it againſt you with the point of hys ſword or ſpeare.</p>
            <p>King Francis the ſecond thus dead did for a time choke vp, not their euill willes but theyr practiſes: For vnder Charles the 9. although they endeuored to ſeed in him a marueilous miſtruſt of his ſubiectes, yet began the eſtates at Orleance to taſte them ſo neere, and to go about to make them ſpue vp the treaſures that they had ſwallowed, that their beſt waywas in haſt to folow Tiberius Gracchus one of the plagues of Rome, who perceiuing that the ſenate were fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of his proceſſe ſtrooke ſaile quietly, ſo that they thought it beſt to ſhip into Lorraine, and thence into Germany, where they promiſed the Princes of the Empire to frame the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the confeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ausbourg, which the Card. openly allowed and preached in the towne of Sauerne, ſhewing the greater teſtimonie of his conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the rich gifts that he beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius the D. of Wittemberges miniſter, wherein theſe ij. fugitiues made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues like vnto The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramenes ſlipper which ferued for either foote.</p>
            <p>But what? the hard fortune of France ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, called the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe to the end to goe forward with their game and make an end of the ſet: yea
<pb facs="tcp:21582:12"/> it placed them in the chiefeſt degrees, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the good example of the ancients, who ſhut vp the gates of honour againſt ſuch as yeelded no accompt of their adminiſtration: vpon which ground Diodetus and Aeſchines formed their complaint againſt Cteſipho, at whoſe inſtance the Athenians had beſtowed a Crowne of gold<note place="margin">Plut. in the liues of the 10 Orators.</note> vpon Demoſthenes, before they called him to accompt of the office that was committed to him for the reparation of the walles of Athens: which did import a blowe and alteration in the lawes, which permitted not thoſe that were accomptable ſo much as to giue any thing to the Gods, neither, as ſayd the Emperour An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toninus, to proceed to any dignitie in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. Out of this reuocation as out of<note place="margin">Tit. de debit. Ciuit. l. 1. C.</note> Pandoraes boxe, are come the warres, murders, and manflaughters, wherin they ſo obſtinately ſet themſelues, that in the yeare 1563 they had a ſoppe of the ſame bread, with the coſt of Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis of Lorrains life. Howbeit the happe of this accident brake not the blowe of their purpoſes. For hee left 3 ſonnes in whome after hys death his paſſions liued, and vnder the fauour of their vnckle the Card. they entred the ſame vowe as their father, &amp; haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Crowne of France<note place="margin">Plut. in Silla.</note> for the butte of their ambition, ſo as of them we may ſay as the Romans did of Silla, <hi>That onely they had changed the tyrant, but were not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged
<pb facs="tcp:21582:12"/> from tyrannie.</hi> Alſo for their firſt blowes the ſtudied to feede the warre that was hatched in their fathers and vnckles ambition: and in laps of time, namely in the yeare 1571 the kings fauour reſembling a fayre winde, the firſt of theſe three blinded with his good fortune, and neglecting the meaneſſe of his race, preſumed ſo farre as to aſpire to the marriage of that goodly flower of France, Lady Margaret nowe Queene of Nauarre, which comming to the knowledge of king Charles the ninth, a Prince ielouſe of the honor both of himſelfe and of his bloud, hee cauſed the Lord great Pryor to tell him, that if he pretended to branche ſo high, he would bring him ſo low, that hee ſhould be an example to the poſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tie: yea that if within two monethes he married not ſome other, himſelfe would dagger him with his owne hands. Theſe threates of ſo great a Prince, cooled the boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling affections of this Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raine, who by hys iournies togither with the fauour of his friends ſo well acquited himſelf, that within the tearme to him by the king preſcribed, hee married the widowe of the late Lord Prince of Porcian: as alſo ſince his ſecond brother matched with the widow of the late Lord of Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>peſat, or rather they both married the great goods of theſe two Ladies, thereby to ſet a couler vpon their ſmale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. To enter into the diſcourſe of thoſe tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies,
<pb facs="tcp:21582:13"/> which at their inſtance were played du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the raigne of king Charles the ninth, were to refreſh a wound which yet bleedeth to freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and who can without teares looke vpon our France ſo tainted in bloud, cruelty, deſtruction, and diſloyaltie? In the ende the Cardinall, whoſe life full of diſcretion ſtunck euen among the Anheiſtes and Epicures, aſcending into A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uignon left the Triumuirat of his nephewes, who bring formed after his lore, haue no whit belied his actions, not ſo much as to admit anie companion of court, or not to hate thoſe in whom his maieſtie had fixed his affection: The Lord of Ho being gotten farre into the Kinges fauour had a wry looke: out hee ſo well huſbanded his fortune, that they could catch no hold in he Lord of S. Maigrin did they mortal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puſh with their hornes, yea euen vnder the gates of the Lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re: But the vicount of Ribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rac hauing for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eathes of the Lords of Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu and Maugiron encurred the kinges indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wounded as he was could finde no better ſanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ie then the houſe of the Guyſes, who ſeemed a ſufficio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t contrepoiſe againſt the kings authoritie. Afterwarde, becauſe the late Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur was a troubleſome thorne in their foote, they framed a match againſt him: The bloud of Salcedo executed at Paris yet ſpeaketh, and the truth of his depoſition appeareth plainely in
<pb facs="tcp:21582:13"/> theſe commotions. What is it not therfore, that as occaſions haue fallen out, they haue not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſed againſt Fraunce? What Prince, what greatnes haue they not endeuored to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. The king himſelfe, of whoſe ſecrets they haue made a traficke, haue they ſold to the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyard, as fleſh to the ſhambles, and vnder coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fire ſtill drawing againſt him, they haue put in vre whatſoeuer wicked inuentions their euill angell hath to them preſented, whereby to cauſe their paſſions to beare ſwaye, if not in calme and faire weather, yet during the tempeſt, amongſt the blood, murder, crueltie, deſolation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of this poore eſtate: witneſſe a Ieſuite of Pont à-Mouſſon in Lorraine, called father Claude Mathew, who neuer did good but in weening to doo euill, confect in wickednes, &amp; one of thoſe ſacred perſons ſpoken of at Rome in this Tribunary law; <hi>He ſhall not bee accounted a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lex 12. tabul.</note> 
               <hi>manſlear, who by the decree of the people ſhall haue killed a hallowed man.</hi> Witneſſe, I ſay, this reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, this ſparke of ſedition, this ſpirit of Sathan, who in two or three of his voyages into Italy &amp; Spayne, hath in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ited the Pope, king Philip, and the Sauoyan to the deſtruction of France: and withall you Frenchmen, to the ende to vſe you as vipers againſt our common mother, to make you bath your ſelues in your owne bloud, to change your curteſie into crueltie, your fidelitie
<pb facs="tcp:21582:14"/> into diſloyaltie: to be briefe, of the faire face of Fraunce to make a horrible and fearefull ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of death, to conuert her body into a graue, her townes into churchyards, her caſtles into broken walles, her fieldes into butcheries, her trees into gibets, her riuers into bloud, her life into pitifull, horrible, and fearefull death: to ſuch purpoſes, I ſay, ſo furious, tragicall, and bloody, do they loud and ſhrill ſound out, that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of the ſtocke of Charlemaine, and that euer ſince Lothair, our kings haue their tables couered through the vniuſt vſurpation of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, &amp; with the expence of their race the lawful inheritour of this crowne. Here doo I deſire all good Frenchmen to marke one practiſe of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quine the proud, who determining to rob Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius Tullius of the kingdome of Rome, began by bewitching the people with the diſcourſe of his race, and by repeating to them, how that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of king Tarquine his father woful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly murdered, Seruius had ouerthwartly practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſoueraigntie: ſo that the fathers lulled on ſleepe with his faire words, &amp; the youth ſnared with the preſents wherewith he laid a bridge to to his purpoſes, he ſo far ſlacked the bridle of his ambition, accompanied with raſhnes, that in full ſenate ſeizing vpon Seruius by the body, he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him out of the chamber, &amp; caſt him downe the ſtaires. A tragicall &amp; pitifull example, ſuch a
<pb facs="tcp:21582:14"/> one as might ſtand Fraunce in ſtead for a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wake, now that it is thus baied at with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts on euery ſide: but particularly the king, whoſe greatnes with like tooles as that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Seruius was ouerthrowne, they now vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine. And king Clouys vnderſtanding that a Lord of Artoys named Cannacare, puffed vp with wealth, gaue out that he came of Clodio the hairy, &amp; ſo was lawfull heire of the crowne, being not only quicke of hearing, but alſo ielous of his greatnes, cauſed that ſower of lies, &amp; al his progeny to be rooted out. In the meane time, leaſt the people being tickliſh &amp; itching at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry new deuiſe, ſhould ſuffer themſelues to be led away with the perſwaſions of theſe abuſers, I would demaund of you Lorraines, what is the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of your prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded right? you ſay that Hugh Capet by force carried away the crowne from Charles of Lorraine, vnckle to Lewis the 5. in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the race of Charlemain ended, &amp; that you are come of the ſtocke of Charles: If it were ſo, why did you lately make the card. of Burbo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your banner, as he that was fitteſt to ſucceed in this realme? was it not to ſhew that you could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree but in contrarieties? or rather to imitate the wren, who hearing that the birds made a match who ſhuld be firſt in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hid himſelf vnder the eagles wing, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence he crept out in ſo good time, that he gat the title of king? you ſay that
<pb facs="tcp:21582:15"/> Charles of Lorraine had but one ſonne, named Ottho, and that this Ottho had but a daughter. We haue inough of this one diſtaffe to beat you withall, wee, I ſay, who are freed from the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens gouernment, who ſtoppe not vnder the empire of women, through the benefite of the Salike lawe, a lawe that is the onely oracle of France, bought with the price of our aunceſtors bloud, with the deſtruction of our townes, with the decay of our houſes, and with the loſſe of two wretched battailes Creſſy and Poictiers: a law that preſerueth vs from the dominion of ſtrangers, and that cutteth off all forraine faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and kindes of life, which long ſince had fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ours with baſtardy, ſith it is much eaſier to know a fault in nature, then any vnlikelines be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Prince and the ſubiect, as ſaide The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odorike king of the Gothes in his writing to the Senate of Rome. But becauſe the enemies of this Realme, and among others our ſelues do reiect this ſo holy, ſacred, and hitherto inuiolable a law, as ſome ſhadow, dreame, or bugbeare, I pray you caſt your view vppon cuſtome time out of mind practiſed in Fraunce, and that which hath no leſſe force then all the lawes in the world, euen by the ſaying of the Lawyers, <hi>Thinges brought in by auncient cuſtome doo ſeeme more iuſt then thoſe that are commaunded by lawes.</hi> Childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert left two daughters, Cherebert three, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tran
<pb facs="tcp:21582:15"/> nine, Lewis Hutin one, who ſucceeded in the Realme of Nauarre, but not of France: Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip the long, three, who neuer quarrelled for the crowne, to the which in proceſſe of time ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Lewis the 12. who excluded Lady Anne &amp; Lady Ione, the daughters of king Lewis the 11. and ſiſters to Charles the 8. &amp; king Francis the 9. ſet it vpon his head, but not in the right of his wife Queene Claude daughter to king Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is the 12. Hereto adde that the whole doth ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily retaine the nature of his country, ſo that the crowne cannot fall to the diſtaffe, ſith that the propertie of the prouiſions of the yongers of the houſe of France, dooth euer in default in heires males returne to the crowne: and with that condition did Lewis the 8. in February 1223. indue his brother king Philip of Fraunce, Earle of Bologne, and by his will dated in Iune 1525. left Artois to his ſecond ſonne, Aniow and Maine to the third, Poictou and Auuergne to the fourth, with condition, for default of heyres males to returne to the crowne. The like did S. Lewis in March 1268. with the Countie of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lois to his fifth ſonne Iohn of France, alſo Philip the faire in December 1311. to Philip the long his ſecond ſonne, after whoſe deceaſe without heires male, his daughter Ione of France wife to Eudo the 4. D. of Burgondy, inſtantly challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the poſſeſſory endowment of her father a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:21582:16"/> Charles the 4. was ouerthrowne by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Parliament dated the 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. of February 1322. This cuſtome beeing of it ſelfe ſtrong i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, is accompanied with a deciſion of the law. <hi>If the Intruders ſucceſſors doo for the ſpace of one hundred yeares holde the ſouereigntie, in ſuch caſe the preſcription of ſo long yeares may ſerue for a title:</hi> namely, if there be no oppoſition or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the ſubiects to the contrary, as that of the tribune Aquila, who tooke away the crowne that had beene ſet vpon Caeſars image: ſo as the ſucceſſors of Hugh Capet hauing bin maiſters of this crowne euer ſince the yeare 997. haue too important an exception againſt theſe Carlingues. But vtterly to ſhut vp their mouthes, we doo in truth ſay, that our kinges are of the bloud of Charlemaine, whoſe race hauing fayled in ſeuen geuerations after Capet, was renued in the perſon of king Lewis the 8. For Philip Auguſt, or <hi>Giuen of God,</hi> in the yeare 1180. at Bapaulines marryed Iſabell the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Baldwin the 4. of that name, Earle of Henault, who was deſcended of Hermengarde Counteſſe of Namure, &amp; daughter to Charles the ſimple, from whoſe ſucceſſors Hugh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet tooke the right of the crowne: of which marriage of king Philip and Lady Iſabell, was borne the 6. of September 1587. king Lewis the 8. father to S. Lewis, out of whom as out of
<pb facs="tcp:21582:16"/> a nurſery of plants, are iſſued the noble families of Valois and Bourbon. Yea I will ſay more, namely, that the Guyſes cannot be of the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Charles of Lorraine, the brother of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thair the 33. king of France, &amp; vnckle to Lewis the 5. neither conſequently of Charlemaine: for it is but 120. yeares ſince the race of Vaudemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tooke lande in the houſe of Lorraine, which in leſſe then 460. yeares hath fallen in ſeuen ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall families, namely, from the houſe of Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine into the houſe of Ardenne 1005. fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the houſe of Arden into the houſe of Bologne 1089. fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the houſe of Bologne into the houſe of Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg, from the houſe of Lembourg into the houſe of Louuain 1106. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in tract of time Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>né K. of Sicile, ſonne to Lewis of Aniou, maryed the heire of Lorraine, by whom he left a ſon na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Iohn, &amp; a daughter named Yolande, who was wife to Fredericke of Vaudemont, &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in 1464. inherited the duchie of Lorraine, through the deceaſe of her nephew Nicholas her brother Iohns onely ſon: hereby we plainly may ſee that theſe men are like Eſops crow, who diſguiſed her ſelfe with many other fowles fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſuppoſing, that proceſſe of time might ſerue for a vaile to cloke their falſhood: but it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out clean contrary, for truth is the daughter of time. Then perſuading the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that their Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit (a fit embaſſador for ſuch potentates) had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued both heauen &amp; earth, as well in Italy as
<pb facs="tcp:21582:17"/> in Spaine, and that the brute of their falſe diſcent had brought ſuch effects correſpondent to their deſires: that the nobilitie had liked to lend them a ſhoulder, and the people had bene wholy bent to their paſſions they brake the impoſtume: and to the end to free themfelues from quietneſſe, which was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſome vnto them, and to ſtiffle vp all peace which could no whit delight them, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as an infected ſtomacke that can relliſh no good food, they did of late put in practiſe that game which their predeceſſors had kept cloſe and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp, and ſo began to play at thruſt out with the king. True it is, that for feare of going bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot in ſo thorny a way, they haue diſguiſed their ambition with many faire pretences, and to colour their warres they haue propounded.</p>
            <p>1. The rooting our of hereſie. 2. The nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of a Catholike ſucceſſour to the crowne. 3. The reeſtabliſhing of the church in her a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent liberties. 4. The reintegration of the nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty into their former dignity. 5. The abaſing of certaine perſons whom the king hath exalted. 6. The diſburdening of the third eſtate.</p>
            <p>Propoſitions which in outward apparance are good, but bad in effect; ſweet to heare of, but of bitter taſt; wholeſome without, but heauy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. For the two firſt are forged againſt the king of Nauarre and the Prince of Condé: the reſt haue no other end but to yeeld the king odious to the
<pb facs="tcp:21582:17"/> clergie, hated of the nobilitie, and to pull vpon him the malice of the people. This is the redieſt way that they can finde to preuent the greatneſſe of the king, and of the two chief<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> princes of the lillie, and to make that agreement with vs, wherof Demoſthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes warneth the Athenians by the ſheepe and the wolues, that willed the ſheepe if they would haue any peace with them to deliuer into their hands all the maſtifes that kept them. Of the reſt of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they weene to haue a great peny-worth, which all will prooue but duſt before the Eaſt winde, and ſnow before the ſame. At the fame of theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, as trumpets that giue warning of warres, manie tooke part with their weapons, &amp; turned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the fortune of theſe deceiuers, abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning an aſſured peace, to the end to follow a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full warre: ſome being wonne with hope of amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their eſtate: others hauing alreadie followed the warres, and liued according as the libertie of the time and impunitie had ſuffered them, ſeeing that peace tooke from them all meanes of ſpoile. Some that had miſerablie conſumed al their goods, and were ſtill brauled at by their creditors, and as<note place="margin">Cic. in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telinariis.</note> Cicero ſaide of Catelines confederates, <hi>Thoſe whoſe handes were died in blood, their tongues formed to lyes, their ſoules bent to all wickedneſſe, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences corrupt with ſundrie miſdeedes, ſuch as vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by pouertie, were aſsalted by iuſtice:</hi> Such out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtes (I ſay) did willinglie lend their hands to theſe nouelties: and yet is it a ſtrange matter that ſome Gentlemen durſt ſuffer themſelues to be led at theſe mens pleaſure, as if they coulde not but ſay well,
<pb facs="tcp:21582:18"/> neither themſelues do well but in obeying of them: A pitifull caſe, that they ſhould take the ſhadow for the ſubſtance, ſmoke for fire, the viſage and lies, for truth, without conſidering that theſe pretences are but ſo manie ſnares to entrappe them, that they do wake them but to bring them on ſleepe, that they inſtruct them but to deſtroy them, and that as an ancient man hath ſaid, <hi>There can bee no luſt cauſe to fight against their countrie.</hi> But who could chooſe but bee bewitched with ſo many faire pretences? Beſides that theſe fire brands haue left no meanes vnprooued for the continuance of the traficke of their drifts. Furthermore, to the ende to keepe their confederates in breath, and courage, and to make others willing to take their parts, they promiſed vs mountaines and maruels, as knowing that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times things fained, yet taken for true, are of great force in warres, as Marcus Portius, when the Iler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getes ſolicited him for ſuccour: The earth ſhould tremble vnder their power: the Spaniſh weapons did alreadie rattle vpon the frontiers: The Sauoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an did but aſke <hi>Where is it?</hi> The Pope calleth forth the diuels, giueth them the enimies bodies, they carrie them away, they caſt them in hell: The Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banians with their Iauelings, ſhould come to beate downe the mountaines, and to put all to fire and ſword: And as the Conſull Varo ſaid of Hanniball, <hi>Theſe Guiſians ſhould ende the warres euen the firſt day that they ſhoulde ſee the Proteſtants,</hi> calling to minde the fooliſh enterpriſe, though not the weake ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of La Broſſe, who in the yeare of our Lorde, 1559. being by their Father and Onckle, ſent with
<pb facs="tcp:21582:18"/> the Biſhoppe of Amiens into Scotland, promiſed in one moneth to driue al the Lutherans out of the lande: But the Scottiſh nobilitie more ielous of their liberties then wee, ſhewed him that he recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned without his hoſte: and that he ought not to ſell the Beares skinne before he ſee him, eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that as that noble Lacedemonian captaine Braſidas ſaide, <hi>There is not ſo ſmall a beaſt, but is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. in the notable ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of kings.</note> 
               <hi>to ſaue his life, if his heart woulde ſerue him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende himſelfe:</hi> and the Conſull Paulus Aemilius maruelled howe anie Captaine could aforehand tell what was to bee done in the battell, before he had ſeene either his owne armie, or his enimies: either ſituation of the place, or nature of the ſoile: for his part he would take no other counſaile before the time, then ſuch as the occaſions did vſuallie miniſter to man, and not man to occaſions. And indeede theſe Lorrains doo reſemble that great mountaine, which after manie pangs of childbirth brought forth but a mouſe. Beſides, what promiſe haue they performed? Of the Wiſigothes that<note place="margin">Liuius. li. 2. Dec. 3.</note> ſhould come and fall vppon vs, we haue no newes, they be ſo manie bugbeares: for beſides that King Philip hath but few men, and too manie matters in hande, hee is too olde to take counſaile of the young: although through a deſire that hee hath to ſtrike a ſtroke, and make ſome alteration in the peace of France, and being allured by ſome hope to obtaine Marſeiles as a firſt diſh to his table, he furniſheth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a few crownes, which they wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue without waying, to warme their kitche<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> withal: &amp; God wot, whether the poore man who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they made
<pb facs="tcp:21582:19"/> twiſe or thriſe to trot into Spaine, who ſo liuelie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted their affaires, that he fel ſicke al Barbaſt, was any thing ſlacke in opening the mouth of his pouch more thirſtie then an aduocates. Of the Sauoyan what can they hope? He is ſo neere the beare, that his beſt way will be to ſet ſure ſooting and haue a good eye to his owne countrie. From the Pope they can haue nothing but Bulles, wherewith they can not runne far, leaſt the diuels whome hee will ſende abroad to entrap the proteſtants, ſhould light vpon theſe Guyſians. What doo they then lacke, more then Gods vengeance to oppreſſe them, a tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted conſcience, and a blinde rage? For beſides that there be two hundred families in France, which will not yeeld one iot to that of Guyze, the moſt part al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redie of thoſe whom they promiſed to aduance to honors, doo imitate Liſander, who woulde not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the rich and ſumptuous robes which Denis the tyrant ſent his daughters, ſaying, that ſuch gay garments woulde make them ſeeme more foule.<note place="margin">Plut. in the notable ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of old kings.</note> Manie of thoſe that ſuffered themſelues to bee carried vppon the wings of their good fortune, doo alredie make no farther account of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, which is tied togither with pointes, as a Lacedemonian ſayde of Lampis a Burgeſſe of Egi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na. All good Frenchmen whom they called to their partie, in tickling them with faire promiſes, haue made anſwere that they will not holde ſo much as their liues of the murderers of their countrie, as a certaine Preneſtine ſaide to the Dictator Silla, who had put all the Preneſtines to the ſword, ſauing him, becauſe he had beene his hoſt. Yea many of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:21582:19"/> into whoſe handes they haue euen thruſt weapons,<note place="margin">Caeſar. lib. 3 de bell. ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil.</note> do with Pompeyes ſouldiers ſay, that they wil fight againſt the enemies, but not againſt their fellowe countrie-men: of whom thoſe that haue better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of common health and priuate commoditie, do with their eares and valiancie fauor that noble and valiant Prince Henrie, king of Nauarre, leaſt they ſhould reſemble the Argonautes, who after they had forſaken Hercules, were forced to haue recourſe to a woman: So that although a firſt bluſh and opinion, and at the firſt puſh, the weapons of the Guyzes did ſomewhat aſtoniſh the common people, which was as it were dazeled in the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their driftes: yet now it is freed from that feare, &amp; perceiueth that their threats are no ſpeares, that they haue embarked the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues without either rudder or biſcuit, and that their falſe winges that prognoſticated ſo high &amp; long a fight, will lead the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the like end as Icarus. And indeede ye Guizards, the waies of your purpoſes are ſo ſurely ſhut vp, that ſhortly you ſhall feele the ſaying of Iob: <hi>Thoſe that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 4.</note> 
               <hi>plow iniquitie and ſow malice ſhall reape the ſame.</hi> Your pride hath kindled the torch of diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the bowels of France, and you ſhall proue the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon true, <hi>Pride goeth before deſtruction, and highneſſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 16.</note> 
               <hi>of minde before deſolation.</hi> You haue lift vp your noſe againſt the king, and ſhall taſt of the wiſe mans ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>The wrath of the king is as the raging of the Lion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 1. &amp; 20</note> 
               <hi>and hee that diſpleaſeth him, ſinneth againſt his owne ſoule.</hi> You haue gone about to bring a whole ſtorme of miſchiefe vpon the king of Nauar, and the prince of Conde, and ſhall ſhortly, to your coſtes, learne
<pb facs="tcp:21582:20"/> this Prouerbe of Salomon: <hi>He that casteth a ſtone</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26.</note> 
               <hi>at an other, it will light vpon him ſelfe.</hi> You ſhall learne that you haue haſted to outrunne your ſhadowe, and that againſt them you haue doone no more than he, who vndertaking to ſlay Prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus<note place="margin">Plut. of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king profite of enimies.</note> the Theſſalian, thruſt the ſworde into his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtume, which he pearced and ſo ſaued his life. And for the concluſion of this tragedie, you ſhall ſooner be deſtroyed then fought withall, and ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner fought withall, then aſſaulted: for they bee no pettie wretches like your ſelues ye Guizardes: they be Princes, yea the chiefe Princes of the lilly, noble by birth, rich in amitie, husbandes of time, reſolute in all pointes of honour, gentle and gracious in peace, two thunderboultes in warre, ſuch as vſe not vialles in ſteede of trompets, a daunſing hall, for a fighting fielde: or gentlewomen in liew of coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſouldiers: who neuer aske howe many the enemies be, but where they be: who were not Captaines before they were ſouldiers, but ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnder themſelues the Captaines: to be briefe, who are ſuch as the Egyptians pictured their great Mercury by a double Idoll of both an olde and a young man, thereby ſhewing that a Prince muſt be both valiant and wiſe: and yet O Frenchmen, they goe about to defeate you of theſe two pearles of Europe, of theſe two eyes of your body, of theſe two lilly flowers: but vnder what pretences? Theſe Leaguers do ſee that theſe two Princes, and many other Lordes which doo ſtoppe the courſe of their enterpriſes doo liue in the ſame doctrine wherein they were firſt ſuckled vp: to the ende therefore to
<pb facs="tcp:21582:20"/> ſende diſcorde poaſt through out all partes of the realme, and to aduance their ambition vnder the viſarde of common wealth, what doo theſe ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers? They propound vnto vs the rooting our of hereſie: they arme themſelues with the beautifull titles of Protectors of Saint Peter, and pillers of the Church: but it is not enough to haue the bare name, but to haue it lawfully. In France therefore of a priuate authoritie to take vpon them the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of Chriſtianitie, is it not as much as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croch vppon the rightes of the moſt Chriſtian king? Is it a lawefull vocation to be a title? Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it enough that the will be good, vnleſſe the meanes alſo to bring it to paſſe bee good: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as an ancient man ſayde, <hi>It is better to ſtay the execution of a good thing, then to execute it amiſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> yea it is not poſſible (ſayth Saint Auſten) for the counſaile to be good, when the means are nought: at the leaſt, that which is to be commended in the cauſe, is to be reprooued in the effect. Saule was deſirous to knowe the iſſue of his warre with the Philiſtians: this deſire of it ſelfe was not to be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked; but the vnlawefull meanes that he vſed, made it to ſtinke. Theſe Lorraines, theſe great buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the faith, would cut vp the roote of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, this will is not badde, but what meanes doo they vſe? The moſt Chriſtian king hauing tryed all<note place="margin">The Guiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans firſt pretence.</note> induſtrie, all force, yea euen to the abandoning of his life, to the hazarde of battayles, for the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the exerciſe of all religions, except the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Romaine, in the end perceiuing that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of the Church is a worke belonging to God
<pb facs="tcp:21582:21"/> and not to man, did imitate the good Phiſician, who hauing vſed all ſharpe remedies, and profiting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, hath recourſe to the gentle: and to the end to ſet his eſtate free from thoſe miſeries wherewith it was oppreſſed, quenched the ciuill broyles with an edict of pacification, not forcibly wreſted from him, but grounded vpon the onely conſideration of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon commoditie, and vpholden by the ſolemne oth of his Maieſtie, the Queene his mother, the Princes of his bloud, the chiefe, Officers of the crowne, yea euen by the Guizes, and ratified in all his courtes of Parliament. This ſo ſolemne edict, this ſo authenticall lawe ought not to haue bin plucked vp without the like ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nities wherwith it was plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: for as ſaith Vlpian: <hi>There is nothing ſo naturall, as to diſolue a thing with the ſame meanes wherewith it was conioyned.</hi> And yet theſe frebrands, of their own priuate authoritie, haue trode it vnder foote to the great contempt of the king, oppreſſion of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and deſtruction of this eſtate, yea contrarie to their owne ſo ſolemne oth. Is it then a good begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, to roote out hereſies with infringing faith? Muſt we be treacherous to our neighbours, to bee true to God? Doth the true ſpirit of religion coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile vs to violate publike lawes, to breake oths, and to fill a whole eſtate with murder and bloud? But what colour do not the ſuppoſtes of Satan finde to ſet a countenance vpon their actions? The counſell of Conſtance (ſay they) commandeth vs to keepe no faith with the enemies of the faith: by which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, Iohn Hus and Hierome of Prague were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to death, and the Cardinall S. Tulian, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21582:21"/> ſent as legate into Hungarie, to breake the treatie of peace made with the Turkes. Surely they haue reaſon, as if we ſhould confound two ſeuerall que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, the one of lawe, the other of deede: If we muſt breake promiſe with infidels, it is a point of lawe, for the deciſion whereof they alleage the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of this Councell, the execution of two poore Prieſtes, and the breach of peace with the Turke: as if God had not ſhewed the error of that decree, by the tragicall effectes enſuing: for the bloud of theſe two Doctors (who vnder Sigiſmundes ſafecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct came to that Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel as to a ſchole of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the better to learne, if better they might be taught) did ſo cry for vengeance, that Ziſcha a meane Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman lift vp his head againſt many Potentates, a handfull of nouices in matter of warre, againſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of old beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſouldiers: whoſe courage ſurmounted the number. On the other ſide the king of Turkes, being certified of the breach of peace, did put on Sigiſmundes ſpurres ſo neere, that hauing giuen him ſundrie notable checkes, he finally built his great Empire with the ſpoyles of Chriſtendom. And who dooth not in that Councell note ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the cruell furies of Antichriſt, and the bloudie paſſion of Nicholas Abbot of Palerme, principall author of that decree, than a milde inſpiration of the holy Ghoſt, and an Apoſtolicall voice? Or what Chriſtian Potentate liked of that reſolution, when Luther was by the Popes Bull denounced an Arch-hereticke, the Emperour Charles the fift in the yeare 1519. gaue him his faith to come to the dyet at Wormes, where Eckius building
<pb facs="tcp:21582:22"/> vpon the decree of Conſtance, would haue bought his life with the price of the Emperours faith, yea euen at the ſame price as were Iohn Huſſes, and Hieromes of Prague. But there was no Prince but deteſted that bloudie minde, and Luther was ſent ſafe home with a paſport and ſtrong hande.</p>
            <p>Since that time the Emperour Charles, hauing made a league with the Soldan of Perſia, and king Francis the firſt with the Turke, layed in no better pledges then their owne faith: as alſo Ioſua when the Gabaonites had deceiued him, woulde not neuertheleſſe violate the agreement made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene<note place="margin">Ioſue 9.</note> them, <hi>leaſt</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>the wrath of God that they had ſworne ſhould fall vppon them.</hi> Vpon this ground did Pope Gregory the ninth cut off al thoſe generally fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church, that willingly did breake their othes. Theſe examples do ſtande with reaſon, for if it be lawefull to parley with Infidels, it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo neceſſarie to keepe promiſe with them: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it were the waye to quench all hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation: beſides that it is a manifeſt deciſion, <hi>That thoſe among whome there is any communitie of right, might mutually binde them ſelues one to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> For this cauſe did the Romaynes alwayes make a conſcience of breaking their faith, with baniſhed perſons, and ſuch as were conuict of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie notable crime, becauſe by the ſaying of the Lawyer Martian. <hi>They doe participate in the right</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. Sunt qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam f. de paen. Bona fides <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. depoſ.</note> 
               <hi>of Nations.</hi> And to whome Triphonius willeth wee ſhoulde reſtore the gage and pledge, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the lawe of Nations and of Nature, which ſtretcheth euen vnto theeues, to whom we muſt
<pb facs="tcp:21582:22"/> keepe promiſe as did Auguſtus to Crocotas, and Dagobert to the Bulgarian robbers that were ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered all ouer Fraunce: No leſſe to ſuch as haue<note place="margin">Cic. Philip. 12. Saluſt. in Coniur. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telinae.</note> betrayed their Countrie, with whome (as a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſayde) wee may often enter parley, and keepe promiſe inuiolably, as Saluſt noteth in the confederates of Cateline, who by decree of the Senate, were denounced publike enemies. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we muſt promiſe nothing for, infringing our faith, which is the foundation of all agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. For this cauſe would not Tiberius heare the Embaſſadours of Tackfarin a Captayne of certaine theeues in Africa: and the Romaine Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate woulde neuer growe to anye accorde with Spartacus, when he had alreadie ouercome them in three pitched fieldes, and was Captaine ouer ſixe thouſande bonde-men. As alſo the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians by a decree of the ten publiſhed in the yeare 1506. forbad their Gouernours to giue anie ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conduct to the baniſhed men. Now as for vs, we haue not to do with men of ſuch ſort, eyther with ſuch as haue falſified their obedience due to the king. The ſpindle that wee are to reele, is with frenchmen, with whom wee haue communitie of birth, of lawes, of manners and cuſtomes, ſo that beeing ſo ſtraightly bound togither, as well by ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill lawe, as by nature, and after the example of the ancient Romaines, and other famous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the great maſters of Iuſtice, and of publike fayth, wee can not in their reſpect diſpence with ſo religious a bonde as an oath, notwithſtanding the purport of the decree of Conſtance corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent
<pb facs="tcp:21582:23"/> to this maxime of Liſander: <hi>Wee muſt deceiue children with ſmall bones, and men with cates.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. in the notable ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</note> Thus much for the queſtion of lawe. Nowe to that of deede, whether thoſe whome wee terme Proteſtantes, be attainted of Hereſie? Wee call thoſe men Heretikes, who with obſtinate ambition doo depart from the articles of our faith: all theſe articles doo conſiſt in the Apoſtles Creede, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Proteſtantes doo grounde their beliefe: They doo abandon the way of worldly honours: they walke in the contrarie, euen in the path of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and diſgrace: they will not bring in mans fantaſies to be rules of faith, but they promiſe to amende if they may be better inſtructed: bee they then obſtinate, ambitious, or heretikes? It is to no purpoſe to alleage the Councell of Trent, vnleſſe we prooue it to bee lawefull. The Councell of Millaine conſiſted of almoſt three hundred Biſhops,<note place="margin">Soſomenes lib. 4. ca. 8. Euagrius li, 1, cap. 10.</note> who in a manner all condemned Athanaſius that mirrour of vertue, that lampe of the Church, of Hereſie: In the ſeconde Epheſine Councell was that holy Biſhoppe Flauian and his adherentes ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and the doctrine of Eutiches allowed.</p>
            <p>Will you then call ſuch congregations lawefull councels? or rather the diuelles great daies, the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtes of Antichriſt, and the generall eſtates of the enemies of the faith. Moreouer, king Francis the firſt, knowing that the Councell of Trent was framed onely for the priuate profite of ſome, and not for the Chriſtian common wealth, proteſted by the mouth of his Ambaſſadour the Abbot of Bellozane, that neyther hee, neyther anye of his
<pb facs="tcp:21582:23"/> realme ſhould be bound by the decrees of the ſame counſell. The like did Henrie the ſecond, vppon the ſupport of the authoritie of al his parliaments, who euermore withſtood the decrees wouen at Trent, as being of no force and abuſiue.</p>
            <p>But the K. of Nauar hath his more particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions: he is a ſoueraigne K. and one of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enteſt, yea the fourth in the degree of the kings of Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome, yet was he not called to this councel, &amp; ſo conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly there can be no default in him, for as ſaith Harmogenian. Hee is a contumaxe, who hauing had three ſummons or one peremptorie day<note place="margin">L. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia. F. de re Iudic.</note> doth not appeare: ſo that the ſentences formed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, &amp; thoſe of the religion haue no ground: and as the Emperors Diocleſian, &amp; Maximilian do ſay. <hi>The ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces denounced againſt the abſent that haue</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. Ea quae C. quomodo &amp; quando iud. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>not bin lawfully ſummoned, can haue no force in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iudged.</hi> Yea in ciuill cauſes, the party abſent is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarely reſtored: much rather then in criminal cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that as the lawyer Paul ſaith, <hi>We ought</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. Diuus F. de in Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. L. Arrianus F. de act. &amp; oblig. L. I. C. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie re.</note> 
               <hi>to be more enclined to abſolue then to condemne.</hi> For this cauſe would not the Emperor Valerian permit the determining of the proceſſe of the partie abſent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing burdened with treſpaſſes: but that an inuento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie being taken of his goods, he ſhould be ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to purge himſelf of ſuch crimes, as he was char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged withall. Theſe circumſtances not obſerued in the Tridentine counſell do make it void, as alſo the proteſtations of our kings, and the parliaments of this realme, take from it al ſtrength &amp; beauty: what reaſons then haue we to conuince theſe proteſtants of hereſie?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21582:24"/>
            <p>Where they confeſſe not the biſhop of Rome to be vniuerſall, they ſay S. Gregory taught that it was a prophane name, ſacrilegious and a foregoing of<note place="margin">Cap. 16.</note> Antichriſt, for ſaith he, <hi>if he that is named vniuerſall ſtumbleth, the whole Church falleth.</hi> They doo alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the 3. Councell of Carthage, wherein it was forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that any ſhuld be called Prince of biſhops.<note place="margin">Authent. Col. 2. tit. 4.</note> For as for that which wee reade in the Autenticals touching the high Prieſt, they greatly ſuſpect it, and as Duarene noteth, that conſtitution is not to be ſeene in the greek Code. If they walke in darkenes, if<note place="margin">Duaren de ſac. ſand. Eccleſ. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriis. li. 1. cap. 10. Auguſt. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 12.</note> they be blind in that miſtery, which we cal the holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the altar, let vs ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the light &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne S. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hereſie, who againſt Adamantus the diſciple of Manichee, ſaith thus: <hi>theſe three things The blood is water, This is my body, and The ſtone was Chriſt are ſpoken figuratiuely, by ſigne, and by ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Let vs reiect that which Tertullian writeth againſt<note place="margin">Tertu. lib. 4 Amb. lib. de ſacram. Cap. 1.</note> Marcion. <hi>Ieſus Chriſt hauing taken bread and broken it to his diſciples, made it his body by ſaying, This is my body,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>the ſigne of my bodie.</hi> Let vs correct Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe: <hi>Like as in baptiſme thou haſt receiued the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of death, euen ſo hast thou alſo in this ſacrament dronke the ſimilitude of the pretious bloud of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where as they bee ſo groſſe that they cannot comprehend purgatorie, let vs prooue vnto them, that the bloud of our Lord is not ſufficient to purge vs from our ſinnes: Let vs plainely ſhewe them the name or doctrine of Purgatorie in the ſcripture, and reiect this place of Chriſoſtome. <hi>When we craue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſoſt. hom. 2. in 50. Pſalm.</note> 
               <hi>we do it to the end not to be examined of our ſinne, to the ende not to be dealt with according to the rigor of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice:
<pb facs="tcp:21582:24"/> to the ende all puniſhment may ceaſe, for where there is mercie, there reſteth no farther torture, exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, extremitie or paine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For eating fleſh in Lent they do it, ſay they, by the permiſſion of Pope Eleutherius: by the authoritie<note place="margin">Diſt. 30. ca. 51. quis.</note> of the Councel of Bracare, holden in the yeare 619. and of the 13. Councel of Tolete, which excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicateth all ſuch as forbid the eating of fleſh at all times indifferently. Alſo by the example of the holie biſhop of Cyrus Spiridon, who ſaid, <hi>That hee durst</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part. lib. 1. cap. 10.</note> 
               <hi>freely eat fleſh in lent, becauſe he was a Chriſtian.</hi> In that they adorne not their temples with ſundrie pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures and images, It is, ſay they, becauſe Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius thus crieth out againſt the Gentiles. <hi>Whie come yee not to the knowledge of God by the true creatures, rather then by ſhadowes and remembrances?</hi> It is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they credite the ſaying of Lactance Firmian:<note place="margin">Lact. lib. 2. Inſtit. ca. 1.</note> 
               <hi>That God, whoſe ſpirite and power is diſperſed al ouer, can not bee abſent, and therefore that the image is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous:</hi> It is becauſe they be tyed to this place of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Cuit. lib. 4. cap. 9. &amp; 13</note> 
               <hi>The firſt bringers in of Images, tooke the feare of God out of the world, and augmented error.</hi> If their miniſters marry, they do it becauſe we ſay that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is a ſacrament, and the miniſters of the church ought to participate in euery ſacrament: they doo it becauſe S. Ambroſe ſaith, <hi>Let no man be reſtrained, lest while we forbid him a thing lawfull, he falleth to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull:</hi> They do it, becauſe in Euſeb. they find that<note place="margin">Euſeb. li. 3. cap. 27.</note> S. Peter &amp; Philip were married: They do it, becauſe S. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith, <hi>That he dare not prefer S. Iohns virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. tract. de Nupt. cap. 21.</note> 
               <hi>before Abrahams marriage.</hi> They do it becauſe Pope Pius ſaid, <hi>that for good cauſe they had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mariage from
<pb facs="tcp:21582:25"/> prieſtes, but for greater cauſe they ought to reſtore it:</hi> They doo it leaſt men ſhould haue occaſion, with<note place="margin">Platina de vitis ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicum.</note> Pope Alexander to ſay. <hi>That God hath taken awaie ſonnes from Prieſts, but the diuell hath giuen them Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phenes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for other points in controuerſie, if we deepely and fully conſider of them, we ſhall finde that they conſiſt rather in outward ceremonies of the church then in ſubſtance of doctrine, which is not cauſe ſufficient to denounce them heretikes: for hereſie hath relation to the ſubſtantiall points of faith, not to the outward ceremonies. But howſoeuer it be, by the order of the common and ancient decrees, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be accounted heretikes before they haue bin admoniſhed by ſundrie ſynodes &amp; iudged by a councell: whereupon Pope Gregorie the ſeuenth, writeth to the Princes of Germanie concerning the exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication of the Emperor Henry the fourth: thus: <hi>We haue ſought to bring him to repentance, but to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abbas vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perg. in Hen. 4.</note> 
               <hi>our faire ſongs he hath lent the adders eare.</hi> Alſo Pope Innocent the third, ſpeaking of heretikes, ſaith, <hi>If a biſhop with his chapter haue condemned any man of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, let him be accurſed.</hi> He muſt therfore be iudged before he be condemned, and heard before he bee<note place="margin">L. Diuus. F. de in Integ. reſtit. Solomenes lib. 1. ca. 16.</note> iudged: otherwiſe the Lawyer Marcellus ſheweth that the partie abſent is to bee reſtored againſt the ſentence pronounced in the preiudice of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons not alledged. Likewiſe the Emperor Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine for the cutting off of the hereſie of Arrius a prieſt<note place="margin">Euag. lib. 2. cap. 2.</note> of Alexandria, called the firſt councell of Nice, where he gaue day of aſſignation to the Arrians: Martian for aboliſhing the error of Eutiches called
<pb facs="tcp:21582:25"/> the fourth councell at Calcedon. Theodoſius the 2.<note place="margin">Euag. lib. 1 cap. 3. &amp; 4.</note> aſſembled the 3. at Epheſus againſt the hereſie of Neſtorius. Gratian and Theodoſe Emperors, for rooting out the doctrine of Macedonius, called the ſecond at Conſtantinople. And yet do we binde the Popes to mount Caucaſus, we make them to turne Ixions wheele, &amp; roule Siſiphus ſtone, when we call for a councell: ſo that the K. of the Romains, and K. Lewis the 12. in the yeare 1510. could obtaine none at the hands of Pope Iulius the 2. Alſo when Charles the 5. being at Bologne, by his Chancelor ptopounded a generall aſſembly of all Chriſtian Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Pope Clement anſwered him in bitter words, that it needed not, ſith that all ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>w opinions were condemned by the ancient councels: aſwel might he haue ſaid that the ancient cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels were ſuperfluous, conſidering that the holy Ghoſt in his word co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all hereſies. But the chiefe purpoſe of councels tendeth to call heretikes to repentance, &amp; to pray to God in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fulfil the prophecie of Ezechiell: <hi>I will</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 11.</note> 
               <hi>giue them a new hart to walke in my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements.</hi> As it fell out in the time of the emperor Theodoſius, who by meanes of a councel that he gathered togither at Conſtantinople, reduced to the knowledge of the truth an infinite number who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hereſies of Arrius, Nouatus &amp; Macedonius had ſeduced. It is not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore inough to ſay that the ancient cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn hereſies, but we muſt haue new, to conuert heretikes:<note place="margin">Aug. de fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica.</note> otherwiſe, as ſaith S. Auguſt. <hi>He erreth in faith, that calleth not heretikes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> error.</hi> So we find in the decrees that the ancients celebrated the councels from 5. yeares to 5. &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 10. yeres to 10. ſince the vniuerſall
<pb facs="tcp:21582:26"/> crowne of Baſill. Neither is it ſufficient to hold one councell for the reclaiming of heretikes to the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the church, but for ſo godly a woorke they ſhould not ſpare for two or three. Saint Ambroſe was not content that the Arrians had ſundry times beene conuict of hereſie: but that ſeeing them ſpring vp againe in France and Italy, in an aſſembly of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops at Aquilee, hee diſputed againſt Palladinus, who was infected with the ſame hereſie. And that wiſe Emperour Theodoſius, notwithſtanding the Nicene councell, wherein the Arrians, Nouatians, and Macedonians had beene condemned, cauſed them to bee called to the generall aſſembly at Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople. According to theſe examples we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find any ſpeedier way to preuent the pretended hereſie of the Proteſtants, then by calling a councel: they craue it, let them haue it: they would lay downe their reaſons, let them be heard: they would learne, let them be taught: they ſeeke light, let them haue it: yea, if they ſtand in doubt, let them be aſſured: if they be not aſſured, let vs goe to them, let vs diſpute, let vs endeuour to take away the cauſes of their diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Hereof are we not without examples, for when the Donatiſts infected Africa with their wicked do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and that they practiſed all kinds of crueltie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Catholikes, a great number of Chriſtian Biſhops aſſembled togither, and beſought them to grant them time and place to diſpute, and through a frendly conference to root out their diuiſion: then if the Proteſtants, beeing vrged to agreement, doo nouriſh debate: if they ſhut their eyes againſt the light, then let the church vſe her authoritie and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer:
<pb facs="tcp:21582:26"/> but if ourſelues in lieu of inſtructing doo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy: if in lieu of mitigating we doo make more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: if for health we miniſter death: if in the chayre of iuſtice, clemencie, and truth, we preach murder, bloud, and ſlaughters, are not our ſelues the fire-box<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of ſedition, the trumpets of Sathan, the ſoldiours of Antichriſt, and the enemies of the Catholike church? And yet theſe firebrands, without other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of law, would haue vs to condemne the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants for heretikes, and euen at the firſt to begin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them with treaſon, diſloyaltie, and periury: and of the father of Fraunce they ſeeke to make an executioner of Frenchmen: of our moſt mercifull king, a bloody tyrant, a Phalaris, a Buſiris, who ſhould be blind at the teares, deafe at the lamentations, and inexorable at the moſt humble petitions of his obedient and afflicted ſubiectes. Wherein there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doo not theſe mad beaſtes reſemble the curſed Bertaire, who poſſeſſing the will of his maiſter king Thierry, diſwaded him from yeelding to the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, lamentations, and teares of the poore French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who, as men born to beare the blame, or thruſt forward with the calamitie of the time, were bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed out of their country? But God, whoſe helpe, as a matter worthie his mercie and our hope, we doo craue, will raiſe vp ſome Pepins againſt theſe infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Bertaires. In the meane time, ye Frenchmen, let vs awake, and let vs not haue eyes to be blind, or vaines and ſinewes to be filled with lethargy, neither let vs account the bloody murderers of Frenchmen to be partakers of the French church. If not, of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, we muſt by armes ſet to the laſt helpe for this
<pb facs="tcp:21582:27"/> quarrell for religion, who may better then my lords the Princes of the bloud, that yet are not departed out of the boſome of the catholike church? who ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then theſe noble &amp; religious children of S. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wis, whoſe faith neuer came in ſuſpect? who may, I ſay, better then they, take in hande the thunder, the lightening, &amp; the three tined forke, to diſperſe all he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies? Next to theſe Princes, what ſurer piller, what ſtronger buckler can our church haue, then that wiſe Fabius, that notable Scipio, the L. Marſhal of Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morency? And yet haue none of theſe bene ſo much as called to this league: for although they be Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, yet be they not good Catholikes after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the leaguers, that is, ambitious, trecherous, cruel &amp; bloody: notwithſtanding they be euen thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolts in war, yet are they no good warriers as the world goeth, I meane, enemies to peace, blinded with ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſtarued after goods, thirſty after bloud &amp; void of all humanitie. For whileſt the Pope aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth the Guiſians, &amp; giueth the ſpoile of the K. of Nauarre &amp; Prince of Condies goodes, he practiſeth not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of Ieſus Chriſt: <hi>Goe forth and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> 
               <hi>preach, the kingdome of God is at hand.</hi> It is an other leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then S. Paule teacheth, ſaying: <hi>The armors of our</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> 
               <hi>warfare are not carnall, but mightie in the Lord, to bring all knowledge to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> He followeth<note place="margin">Hier. ad nepotem.</note> not S. Hieromes precepts, <hi>Let the biſhops be miniſters, not maiſters: for truth cannot be ioyned with force. The perſecuted to follow Chriſt, the perſecutor Antichriſt.</hi> He is deafe to heare the doctrine of Lactance: <hi>Religion</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lactance inſtit. lib. 5. cap. 20.</note> 
               <hi>must be defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, not by ſlaying, but by offering to be ſlaine, not by crueltie, but by curteſie, not by wickedneſſe, but by
<pb facs="tcp:21582:27"/> faith.</hi> He giueth place to the complaints of Hilary:<note place="margin">Hilar. epiſt. ad Conſt.</note> 
               <hi>What meaneth this</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the Prieſts by priſons are forced to feare God? that the people beeing bound are committed to warde among the chayned? and the Virgins ſtripped naked to ſuffer paine?</hi> Finally, he taketh an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther courſe then God teacheth in the 3. of Ieremy, ſpeaking vnto him: <hi>Haſt thou not ſeene that this rebell Iſrael hath done? ſhe hath gone a whoring into euery high mountaine, &amp; into euery greene tree: Go therefore &amp; cry out theſe words toward the North, Returne Iſraell, thou diſobedient, and I will not let my wrath fall vppon thee.</hi> He willeth not to robbe, to ſpoile and ſacke, to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll all with murder and bloud, as the Pope doth, yea euen in matter where there is but preuention, not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: but accuſation, not proofe. To alledge that the King of Nauarre and Prince of Condé, in the yeare 1572. being brought home into the boſome of our church, do ſeeme in ther letters to the Pope, dated at Paris the third of October, to confeſſe that before they had bene detained in the ſnare of error, is as much as to be blind in the circumſtances of the time and place: they were at Paris amongſt their enemies, who barked at their liues, and were dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed red in the bloud of their ſeruants, yea euen in the time that the Frenchman was the cruell butcher &amp; bloody murderer of Frenchmen: that the father cut his ſons throat, that the mother ſlew the daughter, that the brother diſpatched the ſiſter, one neighbour killed another, cruelty triumphed ouer clemencie, and rage ouer pitie: who then at ſuch a time with a trembling hand would not haue written whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his enemies had endited? But in ſuch caſes
<pb facs="tcp:21582:28"/> the lawes of the Emperors, and edicts of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Pretors doo declare all ſuch actions none, as if they had not beene: for that is not called conſent that we force him to doo that is depriued of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: for this cauſe doth Pope Alexander the 3. will<note place="margin">Cap. 1. ext. de his quae v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>met. Abbas. Vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perg. in Hen. 5.</note> thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that for feare of death are become Monks to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt their weed into the nettles, &amp; to marry. And Paſcall the 2. hauing beene forced the right of inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiture of benefices to the Emperour Hen. the 5. cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a councell at Lateran, where he made voide all that by force he had bene compelled to doo. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,<note place="margin">Platina de vitis Pont.</note> the dooings of Silla were denounced to be ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, becauſe that he hauing a mighty army with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the walles of Rome, eſtabliſhed himſelfe Dictator, as alſo did Caeſar by the law Seruia. So that the king of Nauarre and Prince of Condé may iuſtly diſallow the declaration contained in their letters, ſith that the more force that was vſed, the leſſe will they had. At all aduentures, from whence doth the Pope take this authority to excommunicate the goods. <hi>Kings</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>haue dominion ouer the nations, but it</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 20.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall not be ſo among you: Feed</hi> (ſaith S. Peter) <hi>the flocke of Chriſt, not as hauing dominion ouer their heritage, but ſo as you may be an example to the flocke.</hi> Iuſtinian<note place="margin">Epiſt. 1. c. 5 Nou. 81.</note> alſo writing to Epiphanius, diuideth the miniſterie from the Lordſhip, and in an other place forbiddeth the Prieſts to take vpon them the titles of Lords, but of ſpirituall fathers. Yea Balde, one of the bucklers of the Romiſh Prieſt, exalting his power, is ſtill forced to put in this bridle, <hi>In ſpirituall caſes:</hi> and S. Bernard ſpeaking to Pope Eugenius, ſaith: <hi>It is euident that the Apoſtles are forbidden all Lordſhip: how therefore
<pb facs="tcp:21582:28"/> dareſt thou vſurpe the title of an Apostle in playing the Lord, or play the Lord while thou ſitteſt in the Apoſtolike ſea?</hi> In olde time alſo the Prieſts iudged of hereſies, but not of the puniſhment of heretikes: which was the reaſon that S. Paule was brought before Feſtus<note place="margin">Act. 25. Theod. lib. 1. cap. 20. Tit. de he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. c. 1 lib. 1. De ſum. trinit. L. Placet de ſacro Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. c.</note> the Emperors Lieutenant: that Conſtantine forebad the Biſhops of Nicomedia from ſhewing any fauor to Euſebius and Theognis: that Honorius appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Prouoſt Marcellus to be a iudge for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes againſt the Donatiſts: and that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors Conſtantine, Gratian, Theodoſius, &amp; Iuſtinian, did ordaine grieuous puniſhments for heretikes. Yea in the olde time ſo farre were the ſacrificers and Prieſts from medling with ſecular iuriſdiction, or incroching vppon the authoritie of kinges, that in whatſoeuer concerned prieſtly diſcipline, they bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them: Salomon depoſed Abiathar the high<note place="margin">1. King. 2. 1. Chro. 29</note> Prieſt, and placed Sadoc in his roome: Ezechias re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the order of Leuites, and brought them vnto their firſt puritie: Iudas Machabeus depoſed the<note place="margin">1. Macab. 4 Liuius lib. 1. dec. 1.</note> wicked Prieſts of the law: and Numa, ſaith Liuy, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered in writing, and ſigned a note vnto the high Prieſt, with what cattel, vpon what dayes, &amp; in what temples they ſhould offer ſacrifice, &amp; from whence they ſhould haue the money to furniſh ſuch expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Afterward by the law of the twelue tables the whole depended vpon the wil of the Senate, who by that authoritie in the Conſulſhip of P. Cornelius Lentulus, and M. Bebius Pamphilus, did openly burne the bookes of Numa, as being repugnant to their religion: the like alſo did Conſtantine with the<note place="margin">Niceph. lib <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 18</note> bookes of Arrius: for from time to time the power
<pb facs="tcp:21582:29"/> of holding councels, and ordering the churches, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended vpon the Emperors, as we may gather by the decrees of Conſtantine, Gratian and Honorius, written in the firſt Code of Iuſtinian, who ſaid, <hi>That he had no leſſe care of religion then of his owne life:</hi> and of whom we read 17. conſtitutions concerning ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall diſcipline. As alſo our kings vppon the like argument haue builded many goodly decrees, namely Charlemaine, and Charles the 7. who the 13. of Iuly 1438. publiſhed the Pragmaticall ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at Paris: &amp; indeed, as ſaith Iſidore, Emperors and Kings haue the firſt degree in the Church, whoſe nurſes they are, according as Eſay ſaith chap. 49. which was the cauſe that in olde time they had the greateſt functions in the Church, as commanding of faſts and calling of councels, &amp;c. That Boniface the 1. beſought the Emperor Honorius to ordeine that they might lawfully proceed to the election of the Popes of Rome: that Pelagius the 1. ſware in the hands of Ruffin, Childebert K. of France his embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador: that Leo the 4. proteſted obedience vnto the lawes of Lothair, and that Gregory entituleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the vnworthy ſeruant of Maurice.</p>
            <p>But ſince the Popes gat a taſt of worldly affaires, they haue endeuored to ſatisfie themſelues at the coſtes of the authoritie of Kinges and Emperours, whom, notwithſtanding that according to S. Paule, euery ſoule ought to bee ſubiect to them, they haue gone about to bring in ſubiection to the croſſe of Rome, whereto their enterpriſes haue had ſo good ſucceſſe, that they haue made the kings of England, Arragon, Naples, Sicill, Ieruſalem, Poland, Sardinia,
<pb facs="tcp:21582:29"/> Corſica, and the Canaries tributaries to the Pope: wherupon the Clergie themſelues, conſidering that they had girded too far into temporall iuriſdiction, &amp; that ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times their ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opened the gate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſundrie ſchiſmes, were forced to bridle them, and the Emperors to reſtraine their inſolencies, as the Patricians were wont to doo at Rome, who, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth Liuie, <hi>Thought good that the Salians and Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Liui. lib. 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould without farther power and authoritie tende to their ſacrifices onelie.</hi> Thus in the yeare 1046. the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> biſhops ſeing the wound which the church receiued through the ambition of Benet the ninth,<note place="margin">Abb. Vrſp. in Hen. 3.</note> Silueſter the 3. and Gregory the ſixt, Antipopes, did canonically depoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al in a ſinode holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Rome, being ſupported with the authoritie of the Emperor Henry the third. Afterward anno 1076. a councell was holden at Wormes, wherein with the conſent of all the Germaine Biſhoppes, except the Saxons, Gregorie the ſeuenth, called Hildebrand, was exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated as one that brethed nothing but tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,<note place="margin">Abb. Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperg. in Hen. 4.</note> as appeareth by a letter which the councel wrot vnto him in theſe termes: <hi>Becauſe thou thorough diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loialtie aud periurie haſt opened the gate of honor: that the Church of God being tormented with thy newe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, as with a vehement ſtorme, fleeteth in danger: and that thy life is tainted with manie villanies: wee ſhake off the yoke of obedience, that hitherto we haue lent thee, and as openly thou giueſt out that thou accounteſt none of vs to be biſhops, ſo doo not we take thee to be Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall.</hi> Beſides this Councell, the Emperor Henrie the fourth, ſummoned another at Breſſe, anno 1080. wherein Gregorie the ſeuenth, was againe depoſed
<pb facs="tcp:21582:30"/> and Wigibert Archbiſhop of Rauenna, ſubſtituted in his place: The ſame Emperor alſo anno 1083. tooke Rome, and Gregorie fledde to Salerne,<note place="margin">Platina in vitis Pontif.</note> where hee died. Shortly after, namely, anno 1111. the Emperor Henrie the fift, ſeeing that Pope Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcall the ſecond ſought to intrude vpon the ancient rightes of the Empire, concerning the inueſtiture and collation of benefices, kept him priſoner vntill he had by declaration confeſſed that hee had gone farther then hee ought. Alſo by the aduice of the Germaine biſhops, Philip the ſon of Frederike Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baroſſa raiſed an armie to bridle Pope Innocent the third, who had wrongfullie excommunicated him, and who ordinarely vſed to ſay, that <hi>either Innocent ſhould plucke the royall diademe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from Philip, or Philip the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abb. Vrſp. in Philip.</note> 
               <hi>Apoſtolicall mitre from Innocent.</hi> But in the end all was appeaſed by the Popes Nephewes marriage with the Emperors daughter. In proceſſe of time, Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke the ſecond, to whome the Church was much bound, as wel for raiſing an army anno 1222. againſt the Sarazens in Sicill, Calabria and Pouille, as alſo<note place="margin">Abb. Vrſp. in Fred. 2.</note> for going about the conqueſt of the holie lande, in anno 1228. was thriſe by Pope Gregorie the ninth, excommunicate, viz. in the yeares 1223. 1237. 1238. So as he by the counſell of the Germaine Prelates fell vpon Italy, ſeiſed vpon Verona, ſpoiled the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories of Padua: in whoſe time began the factions of Guelphes and Gibelines. Againe, about the<note place="margin">Vit. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</note> yeare 1323. Lewes of Bauier, againſt whome pope Iohn the 22. had oppoſed Frederike of Auſtrich, did by the aduice of the Romaines, elect a new pope called Peter of Cerberie, whom he named Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las
<pb facs="tcp:21582:30"/> the fift, who immediately created new cardinals, and burned Pope Iohn in picture, in the preſence of the Emperor, who moreouer in the yeare 1336. aſſembled a dyet at Francfort, wherein by the decree of the Princes of the Empire, Pope Iohns procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and excommunications were declared voide and of no force. In the yeare 1415. Iohn the three and twentith flying from the Councell of Conſtance, by the helpe of Fredericke Duke of Auſtrich, and the Archbiſhop of Mayence, was by the authoritie of the Councell and of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror<note place="margin">Du Tillet.</note> Sigiſmond depoſed, togither with Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the twelft, and Benedict the thirteenth Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popes: to whom in Nouember 1417. was Surrogate Ottho, Cardinal of Columna, afterward called Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin the fift.</p>
            <p>Theſe Popiſh inſolencies had no better enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement in France then in Germanie: for in the yeare 1198. when this realme was by the Councell of Diion accurſed, becauſe the king Philip Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, reiecting Engelberge ſiſter to Cain king of Denmarke, had married Anne daughter to the D. of Morauia, the king appealed to his ſwoords point, and ſharpely puniſhed thoſe that were aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant at that Councell: ſo that the Pope perceiuing that ſo great a Monarch woulde not bee hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led without a ſnafle, endeuored to appeaſe him, and in the yeare 1201. called a Councell at Soiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, where by orderly exhortations for biſhoppes, the king tooke againe his wife Engelberge. But Philippe the faire proceeded farther: for at that time when Pope Boniface the eight had accurſed
<pb facs="tcp:21582:31"/> the realme, and abandoned the ſame as a pray to the Emperor Albert of Auſtrich, in the preſence of his princes and councell, he cauſed the Bull to be burned, and ſent into Italie Noguarel with an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, &amp; a decree of ſeizure of bodie, by vertue wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee tooke the Pope priſoner. Alſo Lewes the twelfth, whoſe greatneſſe the Prieſt of Rome had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten bayed at, but neuer could bite, perceiuing that Iulius the ſecond followed the traine of his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cies, &amp; that hauing excommunicated him &amp; his ſubiects, hee ſtirred vp the Engliſhmen, Germaines &amp; Spaniards againſt him, did openly by a decree of his Parliament, rent the Bull of introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and impriſon the bringers thereof: and then by the aduiſe of the French Biſhops, aſſembled at Tours, about the yeare 1511. did reſolue, by armes to withſtand the Popes tyrannie, who ſince from time to time hath ſtill practiſed ſome miſchiefe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt France, and as Martin du Bellay in the ſecond booke of his remembrances teſtifieth, Pope Leo hearing that the French-men vnder the conduct of the Lorde of Lautree, had loſt Millanine, anno 1521. conceiued ſuch ioy thereof, that he died ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denlie. <hi>Oh glorious death of one of the Apoſtles ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors!</hi> O the holy father, who doth not onely delight in the miſchiefe that he committeth, but alſo doth euen bathe himſelfe in that harme that he doth not! Since that this Popiſh ambition hath of ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed all Chriſtendome, that the Church is at this preſent vtterlie diſfigured: witneſſe the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of England, Scotland, Denmarke, and Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, the ſeculars of the holie Empire, a great part
<pb facs="tcp:21582:31"/> of Poland and Boheme, the chiefe Cantons of the Zwitzers, and many great townes and communal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Germany that haue played bankerout with the catholike romiſh religion: what thinkeſt thou, O thou Romiſh prieſt, howe goeſt thou to wrecke, and how corrupt is thy life! Is thy holy water now turned to bloud? Haſt thou no other holy water ſtocke tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poore France, rent in peeces with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſchiefes? Is the knife the holy water ſprinkle? Be the harquebuſhes S. Peters kayes? Is thy cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie crueltie? and thy peace warre? doſt thou ſaly for to heale? doſt thou ſcatter to gather togither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? doſt thou prouoke, to appeaſe? and pul down, for to build againe? <hi>My kingdome is not of this world,</hi> ſayth Chriſt, and yet thou wilt lift vp thy croſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue ſcepters, and thy miter ouer diademes. <hi>Nouriſh</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>peace and charitie,</hi> and thou ſendeſt thy bulles poſt abroad to ſowe debate among thoſe that be at one! He ſheweth thee the heauens, but thou beholdeſt the earth: he giueth thee the charge ouer ſoules, but thou wilt maſter the bodie. Thou haſt beene hurt, and yet ſeekeſt to refreſh thy wound. For if any hereſie ſpringeth vp in the worlde, thou ſhouldeſt deale with the mind, not with the goods, neyther ſhouldeſt thou fight with kniues, but with reaſon. If we vſe not to apply to the body the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines fit for the ſoule, why ſhouldeſt thou apply to the ſoule thoſe that appertaine to the body: like diſeaſe, like medecine: like wound, like oyntment: like occaſion, like remedie. To bodily wounds, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long bodily medicines: and to ſpiritual diſeaſes, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall remedies. To ſeeke therefore by force to root
<pb facs="tcp:21582:32"/> out hereſies, is to cure the ſoule by the bodie: or rather to ſlay and not to heale: to vexe, not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: by darkeneſſe to ſhewe light, and by crueltie to teach courteſie. If thou wilt not deſtroy, thou muſt vſe inſtruction: to inſtruct, thou muſt ſubuert; to ſubuert, thou muſt conuince, and to conuince reaſon is neceſſarie. Is it reaſon to paſſe to condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation before proofe? to commit the ſtewes to the reformation of harlots, and the execution of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to the partie adiudged?</p>
            <p>To the generall reaſons of this diſcourſe the king of Nau. and prince of Conde do adde particulat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions. As that by decree of Charles the 6. pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed anno. 1369. it was forbidden to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate any towne, communaltie, bodie or colledge of this realme: beſides that by the priuiledges of the lilly the Pope can not excommunicate either the k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or his ſubiectes: ſo that Clement the 5. by his bull made voide the interdiction of Boniface the 8. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Philip the faire, &amp; declared this realme exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Popes power, &amp; ſo was accounted &amp; adiud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by Alexander the 4. Grogory the 8. 9. 10. 11. Clement the 4. Vrban the 5. &amp; Benedict the 12. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the yeare 1488. the kings proctor appealed as of abuſe, from the excommunication that the Pope had caſt vpon the inhabitantes of Gaunt, vaſſals to the crowne of France. And the court of Parliament by a decree of the 27. of Iune 1526. and an other of the laſt of Ianuary, 1552. declared the clauſe by the Apoſtolike authoritie, inſerted into the Popes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptes, and ſent into France to be voide and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue. Againe when in March, 1563. the Romiſh
<pb facs="tcp:21582:32"/> inquiſition had cited the Queene of Nauarre perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to appeare before the Pope, within 6. months vnder paine of confiſcation of goods, king Charles the 9. thinking that this adiournment touched his honor and the priuiledges of his realme, tolde the Popes Nuntio, that hee would chaſtiſe the authors of that enterpriſe. As in the like caſe did Lewes the young 1143. deale with Tibault Earle of Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne, who had procured Raoul Earle of Verman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dois, to be cenſured. Hereunto do I adde with Du<note place="margin">Du Tillet cap. of the Peere.</note> Tillet biſhop of Meaux, that wee ought not to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a peere to be excommunicate, becauſe we are to be conuerſant with him about the kinges counſels, who in caſe hee had not whereof to liue, ought to finde him. Vpon ſuch reaſons, examples and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges, do the king of Nauar, &amp; prince of Conde depende: and as true Frenchmen, make a ſhield a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the enimies of France, who for preparing the way to their ambition with the price of the poore people, do ſtudie to corrupt thoſe goodly priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, vſing the prieſt of Rome, as the miniſter of their furie: who being filled with raſhnoſſe haue hatched<note place="margin">The Guizi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſecond pretence.</note> all the tragedies at this day played in France, yea euen ſo farre as to ſeeke to make the king to nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate a ſucceſſor to the Crowne. In olde time the Dictator Fabius Buteo, endeuouring to bring into order, that which time and neceſſitie had diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, ſayde that he would not depoſe out of the Senate anie of thoſe whome the Cenſors C. Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius<note place="margin">Liuius li. 3. dec. 3.</note> and L. Aemilius had eſtabliſhed. Who can then beleeue that the king woulde depriue from the right of the realme, thoſe that are called
<pb facs="tcp:21582:33"/> not by the Cenſors, but by the lawe, which is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le of Cenſure? I meane that grounded lawe of France, by vertue whereof the ſucceſſor is ſeiſed in a manner during his predeceſſors life, and without other inueſtiture, is halfe poſſeſſioner: wherof grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this prouerbe, <hi>In France the king neuer dieth.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, to corrupt thoſe lawes whereby hee reigneth after his predeceſſors, euen ſince the beginning of this Monarchie, were as much as to hate himſelfe: for although we liue vnder a ſoueraigne, whoſe handes can not be bound, yet muſt we ſay with L. Valerius againſt the Oppian law. <hi>There be lawes that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Liuius li. 4. dec. 4.</note> 
               <hi>be inuiolable, in reſpect of the perpetuall profite of the common wealth, and there be others neceſſarie for a time only: thoſe do neuer die, but theſe are mortall according to the diuerſitie of occurrences.</hi> So that theſe thinges thus by nature diſtinguiſhed, we place firſt the laws Royall, and ſuch as concerne the ſtate of the realm, becauſe they be annexed and vnited to the crowne, as is this lawe of ſucceſsion, to the preiudice wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the king can not elect any other ſucceſſor then whom the ſame doth appoint him, and in this caſe we may ſay that which Pacatius ſaide to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Theodoſius. <hi>That onely is lawfull for thee to doo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bartol. in li. prohibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Plane f. quod fiant clam.</note> 
               <hi>that the lawes do permit,</hi> and no otherwiſe, for diuerſe conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt that that is obſerued in part, muſt take place in all. But the kings do holde it for a generall rule, that the publike demaynes are by nature holy, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, and inalienable. For that cauſe was the towne of Zikeleg that Achis gaue to Dauid neuer aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And the kinges of Englande, France, Spaine,
<pb facs="tcp:21582:33"/> and Polande, do ſweare neuer to diſmember their demaynes: yea the king of Englande in his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with the Pope and Potentates of Italy added this clauſe: <hi>That they ſhould giue no part of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes of Fraunce, for the deliuerie of king Frances.</hi> The reaſon is, becauſe the demaines of the Crowne is a publike valuation in reſpect of the proſperitie thereof, the profite whereof is made priuate and particular to the king that reigneth only ſo long as he liueth. This cauſed the Emperour Pertinax to raze his name that was grauen in demainiall inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances: that Antonine the pitifull would not dwell but vpon his owne inheritance: and that Lewes the 8. choſe rather to ſell his owne moueables &amp; iewels for the ſatisfying of his legacies, then to touch the demains: which conſidering the other rights of the common wealth, can be tearmed but a part thereof: ſo that if the king can not alienate, much leſſe may he paſſe away his kingdome and ſubiectes from one ſtocke to an other.</p>
            <p>The ſecond conſideration ſhall be taken of the example of tutors, who as witneſſeth Aulus Gelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. lib. 5. cap. 9. could not paſſe away their pupils into other mens power, neither kinges their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, conſidering that they are onely tutors to the people, to whoſe generall benefite their eyes ought to be more open then to their owne parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular commodities: and by the ſaying of an aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient man. Euen as tutorſhippe, ſo the charge of<note place="margin">Cicer. lib. 1 Offic.</note> the common wealth hath more regarde to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of the Gouernors then of the gouerned. So that if the king being ledde by euill counſell, transferreth
<pb facs="tcp:21582:34"/> his realme, the fitteſt to ſucceed may fruſtrate what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath beene done to his preiudice: which was put in practiſe by Charles the 7. againſt Henry the 5 king of France and England, who in reſpect of his marriage with Lady Katherin of France, daughter to Charles the 6. was inueſted in this realme, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the agreement made the 21. of May 1420 Moreouer, although in certaine caſes our lawes do permit the father to diſinherite his ſonne, yet doth this permiſsion take no place in our kinges, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heyres not to them, but to the crowne: for by lawe the heyre is bound to all hereditarie actions, whether actiue or paſſiue, becauſe as ſaith the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer<note place="margin">L. Non mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ff. de haered. Inſtit.</note> Caius, the inheritance repreſenteth the perſon of the deceaſed. And yet we holde that the king is not bound to the priuate agreementes and othes of his predeceſſors: for when Philip the faire, for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluding of the marriage of his eldeſt ſonne Lewes Hutin with Margaret of Burgu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy in February 1299 agreed that in caſe Lewes Hutin deceaſed before he came to the crowne of France, leauing any heyres male, euery younger brother ſhould haue 20000. frankes of rent, the ſayde agreement bound not his ſucceſſor. Likewiſe when Charles the fift in Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 1374. decreed that his ſeconde ſonne Lewes of Fraunce ſhould haue for his maintenance 12000. frankes of rent with the title of Earle, and 40000. payd him at one payment, this decree bound none but himſelf. Alſo king Lewes the 12. anſwered thoſe that demanded the artilerie that had beene lent to his predeceſſor Charles the 8. that he was not his heire to pay his debtes. And king Frances the 2. in
<pb facs="tcp:21582:34"/> the yeare 1559. Ianuarie 19. writ thus to the Lords of the league. <hi>Although we be not bound to the payment of our moſt honorable late lorde and fathers debtes, for that we take not this crowne in title of his heyre, but by the lawe and cuſtome generally obſerued in this realme euer ſince the first inſtitution thereof, yet wiſhing to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our ſayde Lorde and fathers conſcience, wee are determined to pay ſo manie as we ſhall finde iuſtly to be dewe, &amp;c.</hi> Thus, ſith the crowne commeth not by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly ſucceſſion, but by the lawe of the realme, the king can not take it from him, to whom the lawe giueth it. Furthermore we are in farre better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, then the franchized Romaines, who by the conſtitution of the Emperors Diocleſian and Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian might choſe to inherite where it pleaſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the heyre (as ſayth Pomponius) that was char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to ſet them free might not without their owne conſent diſcharge themſelues by an other: much leſſe then ſhould any againſt our willes, make vs to bow our neckes vnder the power of others then thoſe that are appointed vs by ſucceſſion, which is of greater force then the laſt will of a teſtator. And to ſay that the king of Nauarre by reaſon of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion can not be ſacred, or receiue the oyle, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued according to cuſtom by the Guizians ſaying euer ſince Clouis the 1. &amp; ſo conſequently may not be k. of France, is to go about to make the acceſſarie principall, &amp; of the accident the eſſence: for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cring of a king is no part of the eſſence, or elſe they might ſerue for a difference in the definition of a king: &amp; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the definition &amp; thing defined ought to haue relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo ſhould it follow that he that were
<pb facs="tcp:21582:35"/> annoynted and ſacred ſhoulde be king, and euerie king ſhould be annoynted and ſacred. Which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding throughout the whole line of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouing ans the Chronicles make no mention of ſacring or oyle. Clouis the firſt, by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Gregorie of Tours, after his baptiſme, was crowned and carryed about the campe vpon a Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get: likewiſe Sigebert in ſteede of Chilpericke that was beſieged at Tournay. And according to Ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moinus, certaine Dukes hauing conſpired againſt the kinges Gontran and Childebert, did at Briue la galliard make Gondeuault their king with like ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies which were common to other Nations. For Brinion was made Duke by the Kennemer landes, as ſaith Tacitus: Valentinian the firſt, and Pliocas by the Romaine army as ſayth Nicephorus, and Hipatius, as ſaith Caſſiodore. Who then ſeeth not that the enemies pretended reaſons are but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompanied with deceipt? Hereto I will adde, that at the requeſt of theſe Guizians, this realme, ſhould be made electiue, alſo beſides the law &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aforeſaide, the cuſtome ſhould be violated: ſith that by the teſtimony of Agathius a greeke writer, who liued in the yeare 400. and of Cedrenius, who liued in the time of Philip the firſt, king of France, the Frankes hauing choſen the beſt forme of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, had no king but by ſucceſsiue lawe. But what ſtone do thoſe men let ly ſtill, that yaune after principalities? The houſe of Bourbon, ſay theſe firebrands, are at this day paſſed the tenth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of agnation from the Royall houſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the ciuill lawe excluded from ſucceſsion.
<pb facs="tcp:21582:35"/> Marke here you French men, how this young Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander, this beautifull branch of S. Lewes, Henrie K. of Nauar is not alone the marke that the wretched purpoſes of theſe ſtrangers aime at, but alſo all the Princes of the houſe of Bourbon, generallie are bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at. But in what ſort? with ſome breach ſtill in the realme which holdeth of none but God &amp; the ſword. They heere oppoſe againſt vs the lawes of the Romaines: and we ſay they are a-bodie without a ſoule, ſauing ſo farre as they take life at the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of our kings, as appeareth by the priuiledges granted to the vniuerſitie of Orleance, in the yeare<note place="margin">Du Tillet in his collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the kings of France cap. titres &amp; grand.</note> 1312. by Philip the faire, and the decree dated the 15. of Iuly 1351. wherein it was ſaide that the king might derogate from the Ciuill law: which alſo Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip of Valois put in practiſe in the two wils that hee made anno 1347. and in his donation to the Queen anno 1330. the 21. of Nouember. To cut the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore off ſhort: this realme is not hereditarie, but in the family: and the ſucceſſion of our kings is not ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by a written law, but by cuſtome, &amp; her groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded lawes, which doo tranſport the crowne to the next of the blood royall deſcending from the male, yea were he in the thouſand degree. And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding al theſe reaſons, and nothing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring<note place="margin">Liui. lib. 2, Dec. 3.</note> the ſaying of Fabius Max. we may oftentimes make right ſicke, but kill it we cannot: the Guiſians meane to pluck away the crowne from thoſe whom nature hath made kings, yea euen to bring the king to ſuch paſſe that he muſt be forced to nominate to them a ſucceſſor. Although, as ſaith the wiſe man, <hi>The height of the heauens, the depth of the earth, and the
<pb facs="tcp:21582:36"/> harts of kings ought not to be ſounded.</hi> The Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel alſo<note place="margin">Prou. 25.</note> of Tolete excommunicateth all thoſe that enquire who ſhall raigne ouer them after him that ruleth the ſcepter: for beſides a vitious curioſitie, we may ſtill ſuſpect ſome practiſe againſt the king. And in deede when in the yeare 1566. in the Parliament of England, the eſtates ſolicited the Queene to nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to them a ſucceſſor to her crowne, ſhee anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, that they digged her graue before ſhee were deade: at the leaſt ſhee might ſay that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured to abaſe her authoritie: for as ſaid Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pee, <hi>Men worſhip the ſunne at her riſing, rather then at her ſetting.</hi> But to what purpoſe is this naming of a ſucceſſor? The Aegyptians ſurnamed all their kings Pyramis, which ſignifieth the ſelfeſame thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee cannot tearme anie thing good in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that is not proportioned in all parts. Who then<note place="margin">Ariſt. l. 7. Polit.</note> dare be ſo bold as to ſay, that our king being a man is none, either that he is vnable to engender? If by nature the time of generation endeth not before 60. yeares, or as ſome ſay before 70. ſhall wee ſay that a luſtie Prince, euen in the flower of his age is paſt hope of iſſue: alſo if, as Seneca ſaith, <hi>Euerie lighte beleefe is a fooliſh document,</hi> whie ſhoulde wee perſwade our ſelues that our king is barren? but let vs proceede to that that goeth yet nearer.</p>
            <p>The Guyſians by vow and profeſſion ancient eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the blood royall of France, weening to haue brought his maieſtie to haue a taſt in practiſing the counſaile that Tarquine the proud gaue his ſonne Sextus, which was to ſlay all the chiefe lords of the
<pb facs="tcp:21582:36"/> Gabiens, and thinking it an eaſie matter to breake an eele with their knee, and to wurry the Princes of the blood, who cannot be ſo much as ſhaken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the totall deſtruction of this eſtate, do by their laſt propoſitions ſtudie to bring al the eſtates of this realme out of taſt with their duetie, whereto nature and the law of God doth bind them, and vnder the kings ſupport to oppreſſe the Princes of the blood, and by the ſubiects reuolt to trippe away the kings legge. This appeareth euidently: for in propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note place="margin">The Guyſes third pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</note> to reeſtabliſh the Church in her liberties and and ancient priuiledges, ſeeke they notto bring in the clergie to plaie gainſt his maieſtie?</p>
            <p>Hath the church loſt her prerogatiues? Who but he that hath authority hath taken the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away? or who hath authority but the K. onely? But if, as a certaine Emperor ſaid, we ought not to haue any ſiniſter opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of our Princes, who ſhal ſay that our king hath willed more then he ought, or that he hath not ruled his power with reaſon? It is, ſaid Plinie to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror Traian, the higheſt degree of happineſſe to be able to do what a man will, and of greatneſſe to will that which a man may. Now this power is not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured according to mans affections, but by the foot rule of vertue and lawes. Herein do we know tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts from kings, for tyrants will haue their affections ſerue for lawes, and kings haue no other affections but lawes: &amp; yet, as if his maieſty had contrary to all reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rauiſhed from the church her ancient liberties, theſe Guyſards wil reſtore them to her againe. But what doo theſe Muſhromes of a nights growth call ancient? In old time according to the decrees of the
<pb facs="tcp:21582:37"/> of Antioch, and ſince by the ordinances of Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, the Election of biſhops conſiſted in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation<note place="margin">Theod. li. 14 cap. 18.</note> of the people, without whoſe aduow, the vniuerſal Councel of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantinople would not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Neſtorius biſhop: &amp; when Athanaſe declared Peter his ſucceſſor, the people, ſaith Theodoret, did allow him. Yea euen by the decree of Pope Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las. The election of Popes made by the Cardinals ought to be ratified by the people. In olde time the Pope was no Prince of Prieſts, neither was preſident in cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, where the order of the Hierarchy ought ſtrictly to bee obſerued: In the Councell of Nice, Athanaſius was preſent, In the ſecond of Epheſus, <hi>Dioſcorus Patriarch of Alexandria.</hi> In the fifth of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, Menas Patriarch of the ſame place: At Carthage, Aurelius Archbiſhop of the towne: and S. Cyprian ſpeaking of the biſhop of Rome, calleth him but brother or companion. In olde time the Guyſards were no bodie, &amp; of late of pettie compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions they are growne vp at the coſt of the crucifix: Reſtore things then to their firſt eſtate, and ye make a breach in the Popes authoritie, and the Guyſards muſt loſe their grace: yet do they ſpeake of reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing the Church in her ancient priuiledges! but from whence haue they this authoritie? from their ambition. By what meanes? by ſucking the goods of the Church, not for the aduancement of the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, but to ſmooth the way to their pernitious pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes: like as thoſe factious perſons, Robert Earle of Angiers, and his brother Hugh, who ſeeking to wreſt the ſcepter out of the hauees of Charles the ſimple, hyred their men with Church goods. But
<pb facs="tcp:21582:37"/> theſe men will keepe her. O what a good keeper of the ſheepe is the wolfe! How will they keepe her? with armes: as if they might leuie armes without the Princes commandement: who is the diſpenſer of the ſame? Read ouer the lawes, you ſhall finde that<note place="margin">L. vnica. c. vt ar. vſus &amp;c. Taboeth in para. Reg.</note> the enemies Valens and Valentinian, doo expreſly forbid the rayſing of any banner without their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie: Examine the regall lawes, and you ſhal find that it is one point of maieſtie to appoint war: looke into reaſon, there ſhall you know that the taking of armes which toucheth the commonwealth, ſhould not be practiſed by any particular perſon: peruſe the hiſtories, there ſhall you ſee that the eſtates of the Athenian people denounced warre, as they did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Siracuſians, Megarians, and the kinges of Macedon: you ſhall find that the Aetolians forebad<note place="margin">Liuius lib. 31.</note> the concluding of any thing concerning war, except <hi>in Panaetolio &amp; Pylacio conſilio:</hi> alſo that at Rome it lay in the people to denounce, as they did againſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridates by the lawe Manilia: againſt Philip the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond king of Macedon, by the law Sulpitia: againſt the Pirates, by the law Gabinia. And becauſe Caeſar<note place="margin">Plut. in Cat.</note> warred in France without the peoples commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Cato was of opinion, that the army ſhould bee reuoked, and Caeſar deliuered to the enemies. Yea, the Senate ſeeking to encroch that authoritie vnto themſelues, was ſtill withſtood by the Tribunes. There was (ſaith Liuy) debate touching the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Liuy lib. 4.</note> whether warre ſhould bee denounced by the commaundement of the people, or whether the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Senate ſhould ſuffiſe. The Tribunes had the vpper hand: as alſo it fell out when the ſecond
<pb facs="tcp:21582:38"/> Punike warre was motioned: alſo when they were to fight againſt the Hernicques, Veſtins, Palepoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Preneſtines, &amp; Eques. Likewiſe when the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentines denounced warre to the Romains. <hi>The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. in Pyrr.</note> (ſaith Plutarke) <hi>gaue the aduiſe, and the people of Tarent granted the precept.</hi> What lawes then, what right, what reaſon, what examples do authoriſe, or rather do not condemne the weapons of theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbers, who of their owne authoritie haue kindeled the fire of an vniuſt, cruell, and bloody warre? And ſhall theſe bee the bucklers of the faith, and pillers of the church? no, but the diuels ſergants, &amp; ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Antichriſt: for warre, murder, and cruelty are no marks of a Chriſtian, who (as ſaith Socrates the Scholaſt. lib. 7. cap. 15. ſpeaking of the murder of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patie) ought to haue his handes cleane from bloud. And according to an olde ſaying, <hi>We muſt rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate our right with reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then with armes.</hi> Which was the cauſe, that the Athenians and Mitelenians thoſe Periander for an arbitrator in their controuerſies for a certaine territory: that the Acheans remitted their quarrell with the Argiues to the iudgement of the Mantineans: &amp; that the Romains before they tooke armes againſt Hanniball, ſollicited him to rayſe his ſiege before Sagunt. Yea, in olde time, when neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie forced them to the taking of armes, it was not doone without ſouthſaying, and for the moſt part they aſked the counſaile of Oracles: ſo that P. Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius and L. Iunius being Conſuls, they were by the decree of the people condemned, for ſayling away without ſouthſaying: as was alſo Gabinius, for leading an army into Aegypt, contrary to the tenour
<pb facs="tcp:21582:38"/> of the Sibils bookes: and ſhall the murderers of the commonwealth, robbing euen before the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates face, be accounted the pillers of the Church? men that haue not put on armour, but to the end to increaſe their meaneſſe, to fiſh in troubled water, to tryumph vpon the Frenchmens reproch, ſhall they be named the protectors of Saint Peter?</p>
            <p>What benefite, my maiſters, ye Biſhops, do you looke for of ſo many miſchiefes committed in your fauour? you lende your hande to the ſeditious: Is<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.</note> that the way to retire from the wicked, leaſt his ſinne fall vpon you? Is that your practiſing of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullians counſayle, that it is better to be killed, then to kill: to bee betrayed, then to betray: and to ſerue for a marke to the wicked, rather then to doo euill? What may the Romaines ſay vnto you,<note place="margin">Liuy lib. 9. dec. 1.</note> they that deliuered the Conſull Poſthumius vnto the heralds, and ſo returned him bound and fette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto the Samnites for making a neceſſary peace with them, of you, I ſay, who through paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, rather then reaſon, doo fauour an vniuſt warre? For whereof doo you complayne? If you ſay that ſundry gentlemen doo holde Abbyes and Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rickes in commandement, or otherwiſe, wee may aunſwere, that aforetime they were giuen in por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: as we finde that Adolph the ſecond ſonne vnto Bald wine the ſecond Earle of Flaunders, and Lady Eſtrilde daughter vnto Elfrede King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, had for his portion the Countie of Saint Pol, and Abbey of Saint Berthine. Alſo Robert Earle of Angiers, before the deceaſe of his brother of Eude, helde the Abbyes of S. Germaine in the medowes,
<pb facs="tcp:21582:39"/> S. Croſſe and S. Owen. Yea, and our kings, ſeeing that Abbyes were growne moſt wealthy, and were reduced in manner to the forme of their warlike fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors, conferred them to their ſoldiours, who by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion placed in them a head, whom they tearmed <hi>Deane,</hi> which appeareth to haue bene vſed ſince the raigne of Charles the balde, vnto the time of K. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert. If your argument conſiſt vppon the vnfit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions vnto eccleſiaſticall dignities, dooth not the impoſition of hands, and conſecration reſt in your ſelues? why doo you then giue them to vnwoorthy perſons? Beſides, there is no apparance to cut off the kings from their right of preſentations, becauſe they<note place="margin">In the olde hiſtorie of S. Denis.</note> be the patrons of the churches. Yea, Pope Adrian held a councell, wherein it was decreed, that thence forth Charlemaine ſhould haue the inueſtiture of Archbiſhops and Biſhops in their prelacies: beſides that, as ſaith Duarene, The inſtalling of Biſhops, by the authority of our kings, is one of the corner ſtones of this Realme. <hi>For</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>who knoweth not the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Duaren de ſac. ſanct. eccleſ. min. lib. 1. cap. 6</note> 
               <hi>ſleights of the Court of Rome, &amp; how much French blood that horſleach ſucketh vp?</hi> And the exchange of his lead with our gold is growne to a Prouerbe, as that in Homer of Glaucus and Diomedes. And S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard<note place="margin">Bernard lib. 4. de conſider. ad Eug.</note> euen in his time complaineth, that from al parts of the world, the ambitious Simoniſts, whoremai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and inceſtuous perſons ran to Rome to get the honors of the church. If you complaine becauſe of ſome leuie of coine vpon the clergie, we may tell you that neceſſitie hath no law: that men are gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned according to the time, not the time according to the men: and the occurrences are as it were guides
<pb facs="tcp:21582:39"/> to our actions. Wherevpon in the yeare 1171. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wis the yoong had an aide of the clergie, wherewith to ſend the Earle of Sancerre to the conqueſt of the holy land: Againe, in March 1188. king Philip Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, by the decree of the councell holden at Paris, obtained the tenthes of the church for one whole yeare, which were tearmed Saladins tenths: &amp; with part of the like in the time of Theodorike the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, Charles Martell rewarded ſuch gentlemen as had borne the brunt of the warre againſt the Saracens. Alſo in the time of Charles the 6. the Earle of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iou, by permiſſion of Clement the Antipope, leuyed diuers vpon the clergie. Againe, in the yeare 1532. king Francis being moleſted with forraine war, had the helpe of the prelats of his realme. Beſides all which, the clergie cannot exempt themſelues from tribute, becauſe Chriſt paide it: and Ambroſe ſaith,<note place="margin">Ambroſe de Baſill trad. Theod. lib. 4. cap. 8.</note> If the Emperour requireth it, we muſt not refuſe it. Valentinian likewiſe writing to the Biſhops of Aſia and Phrigia, ſaith, that good Biſhops are not ſlacke in contributions: yea in ſuch a caſe the Emperour Conſtantine threatneth them with grieuous paines. And in the time of the Macedonian warres, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Senate ſeeing the people oppreſſed, raiſed a tax vpon the Prieſts, notwithſtanding their oppoſitions framed vppon ſuch freedomes as Numa Pompilius had graunted them, from the which they appealed to the Tribunes: who, ſaith Liuy, declared the Prieſtes appeale to come out of ſeaſon, ſo as they exacted of them the taxes of all the yeares that they had not payed: and yet you my maiſters, doo practiſe enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes againſt your king, becauſe that he, forced by
<pb facs="tcp:21582:40"/> neceſsitie doth exact of you ſome tribute, and tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth you, when he might claw you vnto the very bones, by a iuſt reformation grounded vppon the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the primitiue church. Wake not therefore him that ſleepeth, neither thinke, my maiſters, that thoſe that do ſerue their owne turnes by the warres, as by a ſpoonge wherwith to ſucke vp the ſubſtance of the Church, and haue no other goodes but the wealth of the crucifixe, will prouide any remedy for your pretended ſickneſſe: and to ſay that now they will root out the Proteſtants, is but badly to weigh their actions, and well worſe their power: for are they become Briarees ſince they began to fight vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our kings authoritie? vndoubtedly there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing increaſed in them but folly, and deſire of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. At all aduentures, if they be led by the feare of God, and pietie of Catholike religion, why doo they not turne their weapons againſt Iewes, who do ſcatter the accurſed ſeede of their doctrine through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Europe, in Italy, yea euen in Rome the ſea of that holy Prieſt? If they bee ſo deepe as they ſay in the king of Wiſigothes fauour, why doo they not perſwade him to expell the Moores out of Spaine? If they be kings of Hieruſalem, why goe they not to thruſt out the Turkes? If they be Princes of the Empire, why do they not diſplay their force againſt the Lutherans, but muſt needes come to diſturbe the quietneſſe of Fraunce, wherein they are but ſtraungers? But herein may we ſee our bad deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, that hath brought vs to that paſſe, that wee take our enemies for our frends, periured wretches for faithfull perſons, forreiners for houſhold ſeruantes,
<pb facs="tcp:21582:40"/> and Atheiſts for religious men: ſo as we may ſay, <hi>Ephraim is as a cake on the herth not turned: ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers haue deuoured his force, and hee knoweth it not.</hi> Thus much for the firſt attaint that they giue the king: let vs proceed to the reſt.</p>
            <p>Their bad Angell, the ſpirite of diſcord hath taught them, that there is a great ſympathie or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance betweene heauen, mans body, and a monarchy: that in each of them them there are two principall things. In heauen, the ſunne and the moone. In mans body, the head and the hart. In a monarchy, the king and the nobilitie. That the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of the ſunne or moone darkeneth the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the ſickneſſe of the head or heart diſquiet the whole body; and through controuerſie betweene the king and his nobilitie, the whole monarchie tendeth vnto deſtruction. Following therefore this leſſon, they ſeeke to kindle the torch of diuiſion betweene the king and his nobilitie: for whereat<note place="margin">The Guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſards 4. &amp; 5. prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces.</note> elſe dooth that fierce deſire to encroch vpon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne gentlemen whom the king hath aduanced, ayme? or whereto tendeth the reintegration of the nobilitie in her former dignitie? It is noueltie: it is a wonder in France, yea it is felony, it is ſacrilege, that a ſubiect ſhould ſet downe a law and meaſure to his Prince, that he ſhould bridle his will, that he ſhould limit or ſtraighten the ſupreme authoritie. It is a ſpite to nature, that the arme ſhould command the head, that the ſoule ſhould obey the body, and that reaſon ſhould ſtande in awe of the ſences. It is the diſſolution of all ciuill ſocietie, to make the maiſter to honour the ſeruaunt, the regent
<pb facs="tcp:21582:41"/> obey his ſcholler, &amp; the magiſtrate yeeld to the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the people. And what is all this but to ſeeke to make the Prince hate thoſe whom he loueth: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne thoſe whom he eſteemeth: abaſe thoſe whom he aduanceth: and to face him to will that that hee willeth not? and yet is it the thing that the ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous nowe ſeeke to put in practiſe: it is one of the marks that their purpoſes doo aime at: it is the way that they take to croſſe the kings power: but vnder what pretence? that men of baſe gold haue receiued open honor, and honorable perſons be forced to lye at ancker. Who complaineth? ſtrangers. What ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers? ſuch as of petie companions haue by the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of our kings beene exalted. But admit they were houſhold ſeruants, yea naturall Princes, what of that? If the king holdeth not the crowne of vs, but of God, and the ancient law of this realme, who diuideth honors as he liſteth, why ſhould we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe him a law and meaſure in louing of vs? Kings vſe not to ſubmit themſelues to that diſtributiue iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the rules of Philoſophie, which meaſureth the reward by the deſert, neither to the forme of the Olimpian iudgement, which had certaine lawes beyond the which they neuer paſſed. Kings are as auditors, Realmes as counting houſes, and ſubiects ſo many cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters, whom we make to be worth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time 100. ſometime 1000. and ſometime 10000. Kinges doo reſemble the ſunne, and dignities the moone, which ſometime appeareth great, ſometime ſmall, now in a corner, then in the plaine middeſt, ſometime light, ſometime darke, euen as the ſunne giueth it light: and euen ſo do kings make dignities
<pb facs="tcp:21582:41"/> high or low, great or ſmall, as occaſion falleth out, according to the time, &amp; as it pleaſe them: in which caſe the ſubiect ſhould reſemble the Lesbian rule, which bendeth ſome time to one ſide, ſometime to another, euen as it pleaſe the ſoueraigne: and ſo ſhal we haue the ſubiectes obedient to Princes, which the ancients, as Eſchines ſaith, haue pictured vnto vs by the goddeſſe Pitarchie, the wife of Iupiter and mother of felicitie.</p>
            <p>I ſay not that the Prince ſhould indifferentlie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide honors, for the reward of vertue being commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated<note place="margin">Plut. in Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia. Liu. lib. 9. de 1.</note> to the vnworthie, groweth into contempt: as it happened at Athens, when the people ſeeing Hyperbolus fallen, brake the Oſtraciſme: at Rome when Flauius Appius libertine had gotten the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Aedilis Curulis: and in France when Charles the ſixt, at the ſiege of Bourges made aboue 500.<note place="margin">Monſtrolet cap. 93.</note> bannerets. But by force, violence and open threat to endeuour to limit the kings will, is it not to ſeeke to ſtay the ſun, or rather to faſten a haulter to hange themſelues? For if the the law do deeme thoſe guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of treaſon, that haue vſed the Emperors ſacred<note place="margin">L. Sacri affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. cap. de diu. veſc.</note> anker: If in old time the Romaine Cenſors diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a bourgeſſe for yaning too wide in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: if in reſpect of the magiſtrate it was not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to laugh in the Senate of the Areopagites: and if according to Vlpian, the magiſtrate may lawfullie proceed by a mends and ſeiſure vpon body &amp; goods againſt thoſe that raſhly do ſpeake againſt him: what ſhall become of theſe rebels that doo bring the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects out of taſte with their due obedience to the K. that doo kindle the fire of ſedition in his eſtate, that
<pb facs="tcp:21582:42"/> arme themſelues againſt his perſon, that ſeiſe vpon his townes, &amp; that do conuent forren Princes to the ſpoile of his realme? And the law Valeria ſaith, that in ſuch caſes we muſt preuent the way of iuſtice by the way of deed. Whereat then ſtayeth it, ye french men, that the lawe is not fulfilled? what letteth vs from imitating that good tribune Aulus Cornelius Coſſus, who in the battel ſpying out Tolumnius the Captaine of the Fidenates, exclaimed ſaying, <hi>Is this that periured and breaker of alliance? Is this that defiler</hi>
               <note place="margin">Liuie lib. 4. dec. 4.</note> 
               <hi>of the common law of nations?</hi> And wherefore do not we with that valiant Romaine bring to ground with the ſpeares point thoſe traitors, thoſe periured per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that do breake the law of nations, that doo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light only in our diſpleaſure, and do bring this eſtate into combuſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? To ſay that they wil reſtore the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to their firſt eminencie, is to couer themſelues with a wet ſacke: for who but their race haue troden vnder foote al reſpect of French nobilitie? who but their father and Oncle cauſed that by edict of the 18. of Auguſt 1559. al donations, ſeſſions, tranſports and alienations giuen to Gentlemen in recompence of their ſeruice were reuoked and made voide? who but thoſe furies made the edict that forbad all bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of armes, yea euen the nobilitie, and reuoked all particular prouiſions to whomſoeuer the ſame was granted? And yet, as if the crow had ingende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſwanne, theſe men will build vp that which their father deſtroyed. Yeeld then ye Guyſards your affected gouernements of Burgondie, Champagne, and Britaine to the domeſticall ſeruants, not to ſtrangers: referre the offices of great maſter, and
<pb facs="tcp:21582:42"/> chamberlaine, that you ſtole from the houſes of Montmorencie and Longueuille: Giue ouer your titles of Earles and Dukes, wherewith within theſe 25. or thirtie yeares, ye haue ſhadowed your meane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and walke in that eſtate wherin your grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther came into France, weake of goods, poore of honor, and naked of dignitie. But what? yet by their ſaying is the king in their debt; and by their diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment they do ſufficiently ſhew that they wil not ſuffer the nobilitie ſo much as to taſt of thoſe honors wherwith it ought to be ſatiſfied, gleane where they haue reaped, or gather any grapes where they haue made their vintage: do they then terme this the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of the nobilitie? What aduancement may any French Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tleman look for, when 24. Lorraines muſt haue dined before he ſit downe? &amp; when they muſt beglutted with honors before hee may taſte of any? Or rather why doo we not rather abandon all hope, conſidering that their appetite is vnſatiable, &amp; that they are men, yea men that are ſtarued after ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, thirſtie of goods, &amp; hot with ambition? More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, ſith they wil dazle our eyes with the falſe ſhew of their ſeruices, know we not that they haue anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our lippes with honie, but made vs ſwallow gall? know we not, ſince the raigne of Francis the ſeconde, they neuer permitted any young peace to waxe old in France? Or who hath not ſeene them more willing to hafard this realme for a pray, then to giue ouer anie iot of their particular paſſions? At all aduentures, was there euer ſuch impudencie as to ſeeke to bring the King to ſuch paſſe that hee ſhall bee forced to rewarde their pretended
<pb facs="tcp:21582:43"/> merits, and to let them chooſe their recompence?</p>
            <p>Wee reade of a braue Romaine ſouldier that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed a chaine of golde at Labienus Ceſars Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants hand, ſaying that he would not haue the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the couetous, but of the vertuous: and that Pittacus being by his citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s forced to take ſo much of the land that hee had conquered of the enimies as he liſted, would take no more then he could caſt his Iaueling: wee finde that Sicinius was 65. times hurt in the ſtomake, and had beene in 120. battels: that Manlius preſerued the Capitoll: that Camil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus expelled the Gaules out of Rome: and that diuers others haue abandoned their liues to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of warres, for the ſeruice of their countrie: we reade that almoſt al the Princes of the noble race of Bourbon, or rather of that Orchard of Alexanders, ſacrifiſing their liues in the ſeruice of our kings, haue had no other hearſe but the field of battel: Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Bourbo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ſlaine the 19. of September 1356. at the battell of Poictiers: Iames and his ſonne Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the battell of Brunay neere Lyons: Lewes at Agincourt fielde, 1415. Francis at the battell of S. Brigit vpon holy roode day in Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber 1515. Iohn at ſaint Lawrence field 1557. Antony at the ſiege of Roan 1562. We find that many french knights haue prodigally ſpent their blood in the ſeruice of our kings: but that any haue ſought violentlie to wreſt the reward of their merits we find not. Only we read that one Sigibert gouernor of Coloine, euery where ſhewing his wounds, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaining of his ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence was by Clouis the firſt, depriued of al his dignities: and yet theſe good childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal force the K.
<pb facs="tcp:21582:43"/> to part his eſtate with them. And what king, ye vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable glotons, what eſtate can ſatisfie your hunger? What ſea, ye dropſicke perſons, what waters can quench your thirſt? Or who can fill the perced veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the Danaides? Of ſtrangers they haue beene made houſholde ſeruants: of Gentlemen, Dukes &amp; Earles: to aduance them we haue made a breach in the authoritie of the princes of the bloud: to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre them, a thouſande braue gentlemen haue bin put backe: ſo as Sir, they want no more but the crowne, which God, the grounded law and cuſtome of the realme, haue ſet vpon your head: and yet do they gape after goods, greatneſſe and glorie: or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they vnfolde all meanes to winne the heartes of the nobilitie, and to bring vpon you the hatred of the ſame. For with what impudency can they deny that to be their intent? You (O moſt chriſtian king) are the father of this great family, and Pilote of this<note place="margin">The 6. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Guizians.</note> French ſhip. If the Offices of the houſe be euill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, or the ſhip miſgouerned, is not the father in the fault, and the Pilote to blame?</p>
            <p>It is in manner the ſame argument that they haue begunne, wherewith to bring the commons to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolt againſt his Maieſtie. For they ſet before vs one that is naked of fatte, fleſh, and bloud: they figure vs an anatomie of mans body, hauing no more but skinne and bones, which they ſay, the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men do by a woonderfull ſimpathie reſemble: that we muſt reſtore and make vp againe this poore bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, that we muſt cure it of this wound, that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues will be the Chirurgions, and their weapons the plaiſters: but who is ſo blinde as for ſundry con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations
<pb facs="tcp:21582:44"/> not to iudge this propoſition to haue a very bad ſauour?</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe it toucheth the kings honor whom by this meanes with hue and crie they proclayme a Tyrant: and withall do endeuour to entangle him in the ſame miſhappe as Acheus king of the Lidians, whom his ſubiectes ſlew for the tributes which hee went about to exact. Or as Henrie king of Sueden, Theodorick king of France, and many other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who for like cauſe haue beene depriued of their eſtates. Secondly, becauſe, (as ſayth Plutarch) it is not his part that falleth, to lift vp: that knoweth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, to teach: that is diſordered, to order: that is vnruly, to rule: or that can not obey, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand: but as ſayde Licurgus, a man muſt ſhew a thing in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that he wiſheth to be in others. This was the reaſon, wherefore they mocked Philip k. of Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, who liuing at variance with his wife Olympia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and his ſonne Alexander, was inquiſitiue of the Grecian life among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. If therefore the Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſards do miſlike the kings loanes, let not themſelues borrow: If they will needs diſcharge the people, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leaue the heauie burden of debtes that hangeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their own armes &amp; ſtop their creditors mouths that dayly doo cry after them. But wherein will not<note place="margin">Plut. in Silla.</note> they reſemble Sulpitius, a man confect in all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, who hauing by the voice of the people paſſed a decree that no Senator ſhould borrow aboue 200 crownes, at his death owed 3. hundred thouſand.</p>
            <p>The third reaſon is ciuill: for by the lawes it lyeth not in the meaner magiſtrate to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the greater, neither may he reſiſt the iudgement of his ſuperior,
<pb facs="tcp:21582:44"/> as ſayth the Emperour Iuſtinian, or correct his acts, either take notice of appeales from him, as Vlpian ſaith: yea if he chance to admitte any accuſations againſt his ſuperiour, he may be taken for a partie, and called into an action of iniurie: as Caeſar when he being but Praetor, was accuſed before a Quaeſtor to be a partie in the conſpiracie of Cateline, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the iudge to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned in great fines, <hi>becauſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suetonius in Iulio.</note> (ſayth Suetonius) <hi>he ſuffered a greater magistrate to be accuſed before him.</hi> Alſo by decree of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the 7. of Ianuarie, 1547. all inferiour iudges were forbidden to vſe any defences againſt the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all iudges, becauſe by an auncient ſaying, <hi>The leſser may not commande the greater,</hi> Doth it then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeme the Guiſardes to receiue the peoples com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaintes, to take notice of the kinges actions, or to limitte the kinges will? Beſides, ſith that vnder the benefite of peace, tilled by his Maieſties wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the people were freed from ſundrie impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, what need we now counterfeit Hercules, Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Timoleon or Aratus, who were intituled corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts? muſt we vſe ſuch corroſiue medicines where there was ſcarce any ſore, &amp; where paſſed ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities were buried vnder the law Amneſtia? wold right that we ſhould preuent the way of Iuſtice by the way of deede? were it reaſon the ſeruant ſhould preſcribe a law to his maſter? Is it not the cuſtome in caſe of exceſſiue exactions to haue recourſe to the eſtates, as we had in the yeare 1338. in the time of Philip of Valois? Otherwiſe to proceede to fire and ſworde before wee lay any playſters, is to feſter, not to cloſe vppe the wounde: to empaire,
<pb facs="tcp:21582:45"/> not to amende the condition of the people, which had neuer good ſucceſſe againſt their king: vnder Philip the faire, anno, 1312. vnder Charles the ſixt, about the yeare 1382. and vnder Henry the ſecond, the people oppreſſed with extraordinarie taxes, ſought by force to ſhake off that yoke, but the whole ſtorme light vppon themſelues. Not that I meane herein to imitate Anaxarchus, who to the ende to comfort Alexander, who was oppreſſed with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe for the murder of Clitus, tolde him that <hi>Dice &amp; Themis,</hi> that is, iuſtice and equitie, are Iupiters aſſiſtors, thereby to ſhew that whatſoeuer the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces actions can be no other but iuſt and right: but contrariwiſe I ſay, that it is euill done to waſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures prodigally, and to oppreſſe the ſubiectes: as Tiberius Caeſar ſaide, It is the part of a good ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard to ſheare his ſheepe, not to ſlea them. I ſay with Seneca, the more lawfull that all thinges are to the king, the leſſe lawfull they are. And that the father is not more bounde to the bringing vp of his children, or the nurſe to giue them her breaſt, then is the Prince to the protection of his ſubiectes: But withall I ſay, that reſiſting the power by God eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, we reſiſt his ordinance: alſo that it would proue a dangerous gappe &amp; of great conſequence, if conſpirators might by force and violence proceed to reformation, as do theſe factious perſons that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly do aſpire to the crowne: which is the thing that hath armed them: neyther muſt theſe hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites alter the occaſion, for at whom are they gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? Not at the third eſtate: for as they ſay, they purpoſe to diſcharge the ſame of the burden of
<pb facs="tcp:21582:45"/> ſubſidies: neither at the nobilitie: for it they will reſtore to the auncient dignitie: neither at the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie: for they go about to reeſtabliſh the Church in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ancient liberties: neyther at the Proteſtantes: for they ſhew all fauour to ſundry of them, beſides that heretofore they haue ſought to giue them a deſire to come vnder the couert of their protection, therein reſembling (but with this gloſe, if the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes<note place="margin">Plut. de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. orat.</note> be heretikes) the God of the Planetiades who expelling the wicked by one gate, let them in againe at an other. It is then the king that they ſhoot at: the Princes of the bloud: Iuſtice: yea it is all good Frenchmen that they are offended withall: and yet do they liue, yea they liue in greatneſſe and glorie, and are eſteemed faithfull in their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: loyall, in their diſloyaltie: true, in their falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoode: peace maſters in their bloudie warres: zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to the common-wealth in their priuate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie: fathers of the people in exactions, and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the Church in their ſacrileges: This is the cauſe O eternall God that haſt ſo long fauoured the French Monarchie, that we do preſent to thee our teares, our ſighes and ſobbes: for what elſe may a torne people, rent in peeces with a thouſande miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, and choked with forren tyranny, preſent vnto thee. O Lord in their anguiſh they viſite thee, and thy diſcipline cauſeth them in complayntes to crie vnto thee. Sith therefore thou art pitifull, take from vs the torch of thy indignation, couer our faultes with thy grace, and diſplay thy proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence vpon this miſerable eſtate. Let thy iſſue be prepared as the break of the day, and come
<pb facs="tcp:21582:46"/> vnto vs as the ſlow raine and ſeaſonable vppon the earth. Wherefore, O almightie God, who art the Iuſticer, ſith thy fury traceth like the fire, &amp; that the rockes do cleaue before thy face, plead O Lord with plague &amp; bloud with theſe infamous monſters, who delight only in murder and crueltie: Come vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a ſtorme, and let thy pathes be in a tempeſt: giue them to be a ſlander and curſe in all places. Send vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them famine and ſword: and make them O God to reape the whirle winde, becauſe they ſowe the winde. And you O moſt chriſtian king, weene not in reading this to heare the voice of a mutinouspeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſuch as deſire domeſticall troubles, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sir, the mournings, and as it were the laſt ſobs of your poore ſubiects: Hearken O mercifull king to the complaints of your France, which is deuided into factions, ſpoyled by the ſtranger, and couered with ſores. Is it not enough (ſayth ſhe) that man is borne in teares, growe vp in ſighes, liue in payne, and finiſh his life in griefes, but he muſt be made vtterly miſerable? Is it not enough that beeing bauled at of my enemies, I haue groned vnder the burden of ſo many forraine warres, but that my owne children muſt pearce my flankes, plucke out my guttes, and bath themſelues in my bloud? Is it not enough that the plague conſume mee, but I muſt bee waſted with famine? Is it not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that I periſh with hunger, but that warres muſt haſten my death? Is it not enough that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a fable to ſtrangers, but they muſt drinke my bloud, gnawe my bones and ſucke vp the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe of my children? And if (as the wiſe man
<pb facs="tcp:21582:46"/> ſayth) the multitude of people bee the Crowne of the King, and that the principall lawe that God and nature hath giuen vnto Princes, is the preſeruation of their ſubiectes, wherefore, moſt Chriſtian king, doo you authorize the hangmen of your people? If good Princes doo feare for their ſubiectes, and Tyrantes their ſubiectes, why doo you (O Prince) take weapons in the middeſt of your ſubiectes: or rather, why doo you not arme your ſelfe for the defence of Frenchmen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſtrangers?</p>
            <p>If ſir, there be no queſtion of your owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning in your countrie onely, but alſo that your countrie muſt dwell in it ſelfe, as Camillus ſayde to the Romaines, will you ſuffer your France to be made a butcherie, a graue, and a wilderneſſe? If, as it was ſayde to Denis the Tyrant of Siracuſe, tirannous domination is no beautifull monument to be buried in, what braue ſepulchre may a king haue in a lande all tainted with the bloud of his poore ſubiectes? If, as a certaine Romaine ſayde, Caeſar faſtened his images by rayſing thoſe of Pompey, what footing may your eſtate take by authoriſing the neareſt of your bloud? If, as ſayde Iaſon the tyrant of Theſſaly, it be neceſſarie to doo wrong in retayle to the end to doo right in groſſe, what were it to redeeme publike peace with the life of two or three rebelles? If a king ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to feare dooing euill, then receiuing euill, as the one beeing cauſe of the other: and that hee dooth euill, that hindereth not the doing of euill when he may; will you Sir, ſuffer ſo many bloudie
<pb facs="tcp:21582:47"/> murders to bee committed vnder your name and authoritie: and (which is more) by thoſe that clayme to them ſelues the branches of Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magne: that doo euen by trompet ſounde you a Tyrant, and that doo turmoyle both heauen and earth, to pull vppon you the hatred of the Clergie, of the Nobilitie, and of the people? Shall it bee ſayde, that vnder your ſcepter theſe young hare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braynes, theſe loſt children of fortune, haue with incredible boldneſſe troden downe your edictes, violated your lawes, ſtrangeled the peace where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you were ſo ſolemnely ſworne, and robbed and murdered your poore ſubiectes? Can you without horrour heare of their bloudie ſlaughters; without pittie, of the deſtruction of your townes: without teares, of the deſolation of your ſubiectes, and without greeuous diſpleaſure, of that eaſe which the ſtrangers doo reape in your trauayles? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider moſt mercifull king, that they thruſt the knife into your handes wherewith to ſhedde your owne bloud: that the rigour of your weapons lighteth vpon your ſubiectes: that getting the victorie ouer them, you can not triumph, but in your owne ſhame, neyther gaine, but in your owne loſſe: that thoſe are to bee feared that doo nothing but vpon neceſsitie, that haue no hope but in diſpaire: that looke for no peace, but in warre, and that haue nothing left but weapons and courage. That the deſtruction of the Princes of the bloud, and of the members and ſubiectes of the eſtate can not be far from the ineuitable deſtruction of your crowne: That extremitie changeth humanity into furie, cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie
<pb facs="tcp:21582:47"/> into diſpaire, and obedience into rebellion. That there be certaine vertues that do openly fight againſt the enimies, as force and valiancie, but that thoſe are beſt which do vndermine the aduerſaries hearts, as faith, clemencie and mercie: That the courſe of reaſon muſt ſtay the Princes power, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating the ſame, which when it is at the higheſt in the North part, walketh more ſlowly and by ſlackneſſe maketh his courſe more aſſured. Conſider that thoſe whom with fire and ſword they purſue, are the ſame children to whome you are a father: the ſheepe to whom you are a ſheepheard: the ſeruants to whom you are a maſter, the ſubiects to whom you are a king: euen the ſame ſubiects to whome of late you pawned your faith. And ſith it is accounted among matters of fortune, if a Prince breaketh promiſe, ſith it is a warrant to his ſubiects of their mutal oblagiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: with farre greater reaſon is he debter to iuſtice in his owne deed. Taint not therfore ſir your ſo pure and cleaine faith, neither make it a ſlaue to the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of a few ſeditious perſons. The people behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth you as the ſunne that ſhineth equally vpon al: let your loue therefore be generall (if you deſire to be beloued, for loue naturally wil begin at the moſt perfect) of the true Prince to his ſubiectes: of the true father to his children, and by a certaine reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the children do loue the father, and the ſubiects the Prince.</p>
            <p>If in your opinion any hereſie buddeth foorth in France: if there bee any maime in the Church, let it pleaſe your maieſtie to conſider that the wounde lieth in the ſoules of the heretikes: that the ſoule is
<pb facs="tcp:21582:48"/> a ſpirituall thing, which neither fire, nor water can bite: that for obtaining the victorie thereof, you muſt be armed with ſpiritual weapons: that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is not cured by the diſeaſe, that to lay a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie where God leaueth a libertie, is to make a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall wound in the conſcience: that onely rigor cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not men to change aduice, but for the moſt part maketh them more reſolute and to perſeuer: That religion cannot be aduanced by the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the eſtate, and that the eſtate is ſcattered by the diſſipation of the ſubiectes. And if there be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vppon earth more greater, or more religious then your maieſtie, it may pleaſe you to ſet before you the example of 300. biſhoppes that were in the Councell of Nice 150. in the Councell of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople: 200. in the Councell of Epheſus, and 630. in the Councell of Calcedon, who all were of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to vſe no other wepons the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods word againſt Arrius, Macedonius, Neſtorius &amp; Eutiches, mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters conuicted of hereſie and blaſphemy againſt the holy Trinitie. Let your maieſtie, if it pleaſe you, caſt your view vpon the clemencie of Auguſtus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Iewes, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee ſent his ordinary almes, and ſacrifices to Hieruſalem: vppon Theodoricke king of the Gothes, who being a fauorer of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians would not force the conſciences of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects: vppon the king of the Turkes, who ſent his almes to the Calogers, Chriſtian religious perſons of mount Athos, to the end they might pray to God for him: vpon the Pope, who ſuffereth the Iewes to ſet foote in Italie: vppon the Emperor Charles the fift, who by prouiſion at Auſbourge 1530. gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:21582:48"/> that peace which we call of the religion, and in the yeare 1555. conuerted the ſaide prouiſion into a perpetuall edict: vpon your realme of Poland and Boheme, wherein ſundrie religions do floriſh: And yet onely in your realme of France ſhall they ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to plant faith by armes? Other Princes do liue in peace, and you ſir are wrapped in continual wars. After their example moſt courteous Prince then, change the labors of your poore ſubiects into reſt, and their miſfortunes into proſperitie. And nowe that it ſeemeth God hath choſen your raigne to the end vnder the ſame to repaire the breaches of his church, with both your hands, ſeiſe vpon this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly gift: prepare a councel, a ſchoole of ſaluation, wherein the blinde in faith may bee lightened, the diſeaſed conſciences healed, the darkeneſſe of hereſies expelled, and the truth may ſhine forth: ſo ſhal God be ſerued of you, you of your ſubiects, and this realme ſet free from the miſeries that doo now oppreſſe it. <hi>This ſhalbe the right felicitie of a good king.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
